<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A church-covenant lawfull and needfull to be entred-into by all, that intend to walk in church-fellowship according to gospel-order having tasted the sweetness of that everlasting covenant God in Christ hath made with His people, ordered in all things and sure, and can say of it as David did, tasting his words as he did, sweeter than the honey, the first droppings of the honey-combe, this is all my salvation, and all my desire.</title>
            <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 122 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66993</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">18229011</idno>
  <idno type="VID">107209</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240905300</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3483</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R39141</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">18229011</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66993)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 107209)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1138:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A church-covenant lawfull and needfull to be entred-into by all, that intend to walk in church-fellowship according to gospel-order having tasted the sweetness of that everlasting covenant God in Christ hath made with His people, ordered in all things and sure, and can say of it as David did, tasting his words as he did, sweeter than the honey, the first droppings of the honey-combe, this is all my salvation, and all my desire.</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for Henry Cripps ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Hezekiah Woodward.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Covenant theology.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:107209:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A Church-Covenant Lawfull and needfull to be entred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into by all, that intend to walk in Church-fellowship according to Gospel-order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Having tasted the sweetness of that</hi> everlasting Covenant <hi>God in Christ hath made with His people,</hi> ordered in all things and sure; <hi>and can say of it as</hi> David <hi>did, tasting his Words as he did, sweeter than the honey, the first droppings of the honey-combe,</hi> This is ALL my salvation, and ALL my desire.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Quis pacto credit, &amp; pactum negat? <hi>who beleeves the Covenant of his God, and refuseth to enter Covenant with his God?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>He, that finds himselfe concerned in it, will engage unto it, the keeping the Conditions of it, in His strength, who hath promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to enable for it, and</hi> to stand unto it.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Thou hast avouched the <hi>Lord</hi> this day to be thy God, and to walk in His wayes, and to hearken unto His voice. And the Lord hath avouched thee this day to be His peculiar people, and to make thee high above all nations, which He hath made in praise, and in name, and in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and that thou maist be an Holy people unto the Lord thy God, as He hath spoken,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 26. 17, 18, 19.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>I will Cause him to draw neere, and he shall approach unto Mee: for who is he, that engaged his heart to approach unto Mee, saith the Lord,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Jer:</hi> 30. 21.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, <hi>Printed by</hi> M. S. <hi>for</hi> Henry Cripps <hi>in</hi> Popes-head-Alley. 1656.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:107209:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:107209:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MINISTERS of the Gospel, the Glory of Christ, called, chosen, and faithfull, <hi>pretious</hi> in your Lords eyes, and ever since <hi>honourable.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIRS;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Author, in behalfe of a sew <hi>Names,</hi> charged too rashly by a Godly Minister, (as is meet for Him to think, for a Godly man may be rash, but he will quickly bethink himselfe of his rashness and repent) <hi>to walk by a fancie,</hi> not walking, which is the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring of their soules to doe, in the <hi>broad,</hi> or <hi>Rode</hi> way of the Nation, in point of Church Communions, or Gospel administrations, The giving-out the <hi>signes</hi> and <hi>seales</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> To <hi>old-men</hi> in Covenant with sinne and death, brawned in their villanies, <hi>accursed</hi> by the Lord; To yong-men <hi>strong</hi> and stout against the Lord and His Christ, who never take the <hi>glorious and fearefull NAME,</hi> The <hi>LORD, Thy God</hi> into their mouths <hi>but in vaine;</hi> nor make mention
<pb facs="tcp:107209:3"/> of <hi>Christ</hi> and <hi>His pretious blood</hi> (A simple folk are commonly mistaken here) not as to the substance of it, that is spilt and perished, and if we had it, as some say they have, it could not wash us, but defile us, as our blood would, but <hi>pretious</hi> as to the glorious Merit of it, being the <hi>blood</hi> of God-man) never making the least men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, of <hi>Christ and His blood</hi> (the Churches Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure; for it is their Righteousness, as our blood is our sinfulness) but in an <hi>oath:</hi> To <hi>Babes</hi> in understanding, who, take them altogether, <hi>old</hi> and <hi>yong,</hi> and Babes, are as wholy ignorant of Christ, and of the Covenant of God established in His Blood, as are the <hi>Babes</hi> they present to <hi>Baptism:</hi> This Author, he was saying, made his Address unto you at the first, Craving your righteous judgement in these matters; Also as to a Church-way, and their walk therein, who walk together well agreed in Gospel-fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, <hi>Whether their way is not, as a Causey way, paved-out before them in the Holy Scriptures?</hi> And</p>
            <p>Now at the last, and full close of his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken Task, work of Faith, and labour of love, he taketh the boldness againe to make Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation unto you, Craving your judgement, which, he is assured shall be, according to Truth,
<pb facs="tcp:107209:3"/> as before about a <hi>Church-way,</hi> so now about a <hi>Church-Covenant</hi> (that <hi>Apple</hi> of strife, and <hi>bone</hi> of offence cast-in among the Churches, he sayes not by whom, but he sayes <hi>the hand of—Joab is with them in all this,</hi> and therefore, the more earnestly he craves your judgement in this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) <q>whether, (there being a Communion of Saints on earth, who, through the supply of the Spirit, are still maintaining their <hi>fellowship with the Father, and with His Son Jesus Christ)</hi> these may not, yea ought not, in the strength of Christ, enter into Covenant each with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and all with God, so to doe? Briefly, whether the <hi>Oath of the Covenant</hi> (that is, in the strength of Christ, to <hi>stand to it)</hi> may not be taken <hi>once,</hi> as well as the seales thereof, <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten?</hi> he would adde, yea taken first, if time serve, and persons are so agreed, before the <hi>seales</hi> are taken?</q> Herein he craves your righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgement, And humbly craves leave to adde, or rather entreats you to adde it for him what you read spoken in a ease very different, but not more weighty and momentous, <hi>Take heed what ye doe: for ye judge not for man but for the Lord, who is with you in the judgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is all he commends to your thoughts, which, he feares not will be less serious, because
<pb facs="tcp:107209:4"/> offered unto you with a trembling hand, because by so inferiour a person, as if, (it was a proverb once) he had been offring to an <hi>Elephant,</hi> and not to such he knowes you to be, as well the <hi>sheep</hi> of Christ meek and gentle, can <hi>beare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, hope, endure all things,</hi> according to the right sense and meaning thereof, being <hi>clothed</hi> with <hi>charity,</hi> as ye are with <hi>humility:</hi> he was saying, as well the <hi>Sheep of Christ</hi> as ye are His <hi>Shepherds.</hi> Notwithstanding, his heart should tremble more than his hand, Considering wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the weight of the matter he craves, your judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-in, The <hi>oath of the Covenant</hi> being as momentous almost, as the <hi>seales</hi> are, and they are <hi>Tremenda mysteria.</hi> But indeed, this causeth his feare, least any thing should be taken amiss by you, or don uncomely by him, such a <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing</hi> as indeed he that tendreth this unto you is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>HEZEKIAH WOODVVARD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:107209:4"/>
            <head>READER,</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Ossible thou maist be one of a few into whose hands this may come. If so, know (1) There was good reason, if not a necessity of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this, That whereas there must be half an hundred Copies thereof, we might have an hundred of them or more with less labour, and not much more cost. And who knowes whether thou maist not be one of those few among many, that hast been instrue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to this discretion, To make <hi>a vertue of neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity</hi> in this case also, <hi>proving all things: holding fast that which is good.</hi> Thou knowest (2) if thou art not a <hi>stranger in our Israel;</hi> nor to the <hi>life of Israel,</hi> the <hi>living God</hi> in the midst of <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael;</hi> That there is nothing in the world except the <hi>power of Godliness,</hi> because it is a <hi>God-likeness,</hi> so much struck at (not to say contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted by the good, and blasphemed by the evill, if it were considerable as to this matter, what the last doe) as a <hi>Church-Covenant</hi> is. Now we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess heartily we see no more reason (possible it may be conceived to be, for want of <hi>that eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salve)</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:107209:5"/> why good men should stick at it, we mean, to receive the <hi>oath</hi> of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> than they doe, to receive the <hi>seales of the Covenant:</hi> or than they should stick at this, the going to God in <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>praises:</hi> for we humbly conceive <hi>praying</hi> and <hi>praising</hi> is but an implicit engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their hearts to, and Covenanting with God; for suppose we should heare such words as these, would they not be an abhorring to us? <hi>Ile pray unto Thee, LORD, for what I would have, and praise thee for what I have, but I will not engage unto Thee, I am resolved to be free</hi> (speak-out man, what thou meanest, by being <hi>free?</hi> it followes) <q>so as when the <hi>Prince of this world</hi> comes in the allurements of the <hi>lust of the flesh, the lust of the eye, and pride of life,</hi> I may be <hi>free</hi> to engage to whom I please, which will be to him, that maketh the fullest and fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest offer, and gives it presently, putting it as into my hand.</q> This now is plaine English, and his, who will not engage to his God, that he may be <hi>free,</hi> that is, <hi>free from Righteousnes,</hi> the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of sin, and the Devills bond-slave: for we must engage to the one or the other, we cannot <hi>have two,</hi> no more than we can engage unto <hi>two Masters.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That we may prepare thy eare for that, which
<pb facs="tcp:107209:5"/> followes, we will goe-on a little; Know then for thy good, That neither the God of <hi>Israel,</hi> nor the god of the world, whom the world hath made so, can indure a servant <hi>halting</hi> between two Masters, he must stand <hi>bent</hi> to one with his <hi>back</hi> upon th' other. Know also, That the <hi>Lord</hi> Christ, who so loved His people, as one <hi>sick</hi> with <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 20. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 25, 26. <hi>Rev:</hi> 1. 5. <hi>Rev:</hi> 3. 16.</note> love indeed, <hi>giving Himself for them,</hi> and <hi>wash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them in His blood,</hi> cannot endure a <hi>luke-warme</hi> person, neither <hi>hot</hi> nor <hi>cold,</hi> a <hi>midling</hi> person; he will not engage to Christ, nor professed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly against Him; he will be for Him in shew, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Him indeed. The Lord Christ cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure this man; He will <hi>spue him out of His mouth.</hi> Worthy <hi>Brightmans</hi> words follow, <q>We must take heed, we wrest not similitudes beyond their scope. What is this then to <hi>be spewed out of His mouth?</hi> Will Christ, in whose mouth the Truth it selfe doth reside, take away His Truth from this <hi>(luke-warme</hi> person) giving him over into absurd opinions, and that he should againe beleeve a lye? The itching de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire indeed, that many have at this day, to broach againe to the people monstrous opinions, and such as have been already hissed-out, doth make this interpretation probable. We know what hath been taught within these few yeares
<pb facs="tcp:107209:6"/> in the Schooles, preached usually in Sermons <hi>(there is nothing now, that is NEW, it hath been already of old time, which was before us)</hi> disputed publickly at Commence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and what it is, that was put in print the last summer. I cannot tell what to say certainly of this matter. The event shall ere long make it plaine. In the meane time let us know, That this punishment shall be very dreadfull; for first, Christ shall take pleasure in casting away this <hi>luke-warme</hi> person from Himselfe; for what more acceptable to a man, that is stomack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sick with eating meat, he <hi>now</hi> loatheth, than to vomit it-up, and so to be eased of that, which causeth his sickness? Even as <hi>Moses</hi> threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, unto the Jewish Apostat's, <hi>That the Lord</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deu:</hi> 28. 36.</note>
                  <hi>would even so rejoyce, to destroy them, and to cut them off, as He did before that rejoyce in doing them good.</hi> Secondly, That He will cast out this <hi>person</hi> with great reproach, for an unclean place is sought for to vomit-in. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, That this <hi>person</hi> shall never receive his former dignitie, he shall never be received-in againe, he shall be an abhorred person, as we our vomit, we have cast out.</q> I come yet closer to the thing in hand, and so to draw to a conclusion here, Take we heed of this <hi>Middle Temper.</hi> It is dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
<pb facs="tcp:107209:6"/> to our Bodies. We have heard an health<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full person say; <hi>It is not with me as it hath been, I am not sick, nor am I well;</hi> within a few dayes after, he fell dangerously sick, and unto death: so, a <hi>luke-warme</hi> person in the matters of His God, will grow quickly, a <hi>key-cold</hi> person.</p>
            <p>We will adde but this for the preparing of the eare; If we look that God should <hi>avouch</hi> us for His people, we must <hi>avouch</hi> Him for <hi>our</hi> God. God saith to <hi>Abraham,</hi> Ile be thy <hi>Shield and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 15. 1.</note>
               <hi>great Reward,</hi> and not another for Mee; Ile be so to thee <hi>My self,</hi> Ile approve My self a <hi>God All sufficient to thee,</hi> There is Gods engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>Thou shalt walk before Me and be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 1.</note> there is <hi>Abrahams</hi> engagement. He sayes to His <hi>Israel,</hi> to every one, in whose <hi>heart is no guile; Thou art my people,</hi> Ile take thee for My own, and so Ile engage to thee My <hi>promise,</hi> and My <hi>oath;</hi> Ile give thee faithfull witnesses besides, the <hi>Sunne</hi> and the <hi>Moone:</hi> so the Lord saith, and so He engageth; So must <hi>Israel</hi> to Him, for th' <hi>engagement</hi> is mutuall, as <hi>election,</hi> when it is made knowne; and <hi>love</hi> is, when it is <hi>shed</hi> adroad in the heart; we <hi>choose</hi> Him; we <hi>love</hi> Him; we <hi>engage</hi> to Him; All betwixt God &amp; His <hi>Israel</hi> is reciprocall; so is this engagement too; <hi>Thou art my people</hi> saith the Lord; <hi>And
<pb facs="tcp:107209:7"/> they shall say, Thou art my God; I am for Thee,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hos.</hi> 2. 23. 3. 3.</note> saith the Lord; <hi>I will not be for another,</hi> say His people, as their <hi>Lord</hi> saith, <hi>they shall not.</hi> What God saith, He will <hi>sweare</hi> too, I have <hi>sworne unto David.</hi> We shall heare anon <hi>David</hi> swear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto Him. It is mutuall; it is reciprocall; The summe is this, when God makes His promise to us; <hi>Ile be your God,</hi> He tendreth His yoak to us also, <hi>You must be my people,</hi> drawing together in that yoak, if not, ye are <hi>Children of Belial,</hi> saith the <hi>Lord,</hi> no more in Covenant with Me, nor I with you, no more than children of <hi>the Ethiopians</hi> are. In the last place, and to shut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>up.</p>
            <p>Know (3) That the Author in his last Treatise <hi>pag.</hi> 59. hath made mention of a <hi>Church-Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> And the lawfullness, in the strength of God, to engage thereunto. The speciall service then that these papers are engaged upon, relates to our selves specially, to hold-out (1) the reasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleness and equity, yea the necessity of a <hi>Church-Covenant,</hi> for all them that walk in Church-fellowship. (2) To resolve one th'other, as to the exceptions against it, rendring it, as we could, and was our duty to doe, as plaine and cleare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us as was possible to doe, that we might each of us ponder it well, and muse on it; which could
<pb facs="tcp:107209:7"/> not possibly be don by us, but by making it as le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible as thou see'st it. Also</p>
            <p>Sith than (4) it hath chanced so, That thou hast met with it, much good may it do thee. Every private person should be a publick good; then no publick person should be a private good, for that were as sad as it is uncomely. We intend but this, If a person or thing be good, the more common, the more good.</p>
            <p>We will point to his words and close with them here and hereafter, where we shall set them down, having such full weight in the ballance of the Sanctuary; <q>The Lord give us to beleeve, yea to taste the goodness and sweetness, of this engageing our selves <hi>the Lords people,</hi> and we shall be humbled before the Lord, that we ever with-stood it.</q>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:107209:8"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:107209:8"/>
            <head>The engagement of fellow-hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers to the Truth, walking together in Gospel fellowship.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Ten Questions, with their Answers, are premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, whereby to give a good understanding, as to this engagement.</hi> (1) <hi>What it is.</hi> (2) <hi>How lawfull it is.</hi> (3) <hi>What man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of persons they must be, who doe engage.</hi> (4) <hi>What they must engage-in; In whose strength, and for what ends.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q:</hi> I. <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat it is to engage; or what is this engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing work?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Answ.</hi> It is a solemne free and voluntary promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, or avowing our selves, the servants of the most High God, <hi>subscribing</hi> our names <note n="a" place="margin">Isa. 44. 5.</note>, and <hi>engageing</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Jer. 20. 21.</note> our soules unto Him, to hold <hi>fellowship with Him,</hi> walking together as friends, and well <hi>agreed</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Amos 3. 3.</note>. More briefly, it is <note place="margin">c 1 Joh. 1. 3.</note> this, An engageing our hearts for our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Christ:</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all that most, which is most contrary to Him. In a word, It is an avouching of God for our God, and our selves the <hi>Lords</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chro. 23. 16.</note>
                  <hi>people.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the clearing this first Question we will take-in what may <hi>scruple</hi> or offend the <hi>weak</hi> and in passage, remove it, as we can. And</p>
               <p>
                  <q>If this engageing our selves the <hi>Lords people</hi> must be <hi>free</hi> and <hi>voluntary,</hi> what say we to that <hi>Covenant,</hi> which was thrust upon the people, every one knowes where?</q>
               </p>
               <p>To this we say (1) That we would say nothing to it at all,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:107209:9"/> aske them, who can better resolve you than can the most knowing among us Yet for the sake of them that are <hi>weak,</hi> we would say this (2) That this is nothing to the business or Question in hand: we are holding forth a <hi>Church-Covenant,</hi> and how reasonable a thing it is, That all, who are truely and indeed of the <hi>Church of Christ,</hi> and walking in fellowship together, should <hi>engage to Christ.</hi> (3) We would say for our own satisfaction, who are as <hi>weak</hi> as the weakest (others may say and think as they please) That <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> had so many <hi>ingredients</hi> in it, it was so full of mixture, as that an haile, strong and healthy stomack might, haply nauseat at it. Therefore (4) It should not, we humbly conceive, have been pressed upon the people, specially because the chiefe <hi>Article</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, or <hi>Head</hi> thereof was not understood by us (the most of us) and then we could not enter into Covenant about it, nor <hi>sweare in judgement.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But had it been a <hi>simple</hi> Covenant, we meane with-out mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as <hi>Asa's</hi> was <hi>to seek the LORD GOD of Israel with all</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Chro. 15. 12 23. 16.</note>
                  <hi>their heart, and with all their soule;</hi> or that they should be the <hi>LORDS people</hi> as <hi>Jehojada's</hi> was, we would Querie here, might it have been pressed upon the people? The Answer to this makes something for the clearing the busines or question in hand; but we will take it-in to our answer unto the sixt Question, onely this we would say more here, because we are upon engageing; What may be said to that engagement charged upon the people some yeares since? To this we say, much more might be said, for the <hi>pressing</hi> of that <hi>engagement</hi> (though some thought themselves then, and so doe now, oppressed by it, grossly if not sinfully mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staken, we think) than can be said for the pressing, of the other said <hi>Covenant,</hi> which was, we know not well what it was, but partly <hi>Religious</hi> it was, and partly <hi>Civill.</hi> But this <hi>engagement</hi> was meerely <hi>Civill;</hi> and as <hi>reasonable</hi> as <hi>reason</hi> it selfe, That our <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers</hi> engageing to us to doe all they could for us, we should againe engage to all we could for them, at least, to doe nothing against them. Why? the <hi>Bramble</hi> it self would have the <hi>Trees engage</hi> to <hi>Him,</hi> the best thing they had, their <hi>Faith,</hi> and their <hi>Troth,</hi> as we too commonly say, their very <hi>Jewell,</hi> and he is a beggarly man, that layes that to pawn; <hi>If in truth ye anoint me King over you</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Judg 9. 15.</note>
                  <hi>come and put your TRƲST under my shadow;</hi> It riseth to as
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:107209:9"/> much as this; <hi>If you will make me your Ruler or Parliament Man,</hi> you must engage to Me your <hi>Trust;</hi> We must come up to the termes of the <hi>Bramble,</hi> in <hi>Civill</hi> matters or civill <hi>Trust.</hi> Surely it was but <hi>right</hi> and <hi>good,</hi> That our Rulers should engage us to as much as the <hi>Bramble,</hi> did the other <hi>Trees.</hi> If they will give him the Title of a King, they must give him, the honour of a King.</p>
               <p>But now, which we would think might answer all that can be said against our engageing to God, whereof more will be said anon. If we take Him for our <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Christ,</hi> all the Reason in the world we should engage our <hi>Trust</hi> unto Him, and that is our <hi>All,</hi> a serious profession of our faithfullness to God, and <hi>adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> to His wayes. Look what the Man is, such is his <hi>Trust,</hi> if he be earthly and sensuall, his <hi>Trust</hi> is the same; If heavenly and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, such is his <hi>Trust</hi> also; Holy men as well as Holy women, are described by this, <hi>They Trusted in God;</hi> which <hi>Trust</hi> in a large <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 5.</note> sense, is put for the whole Compasse of our duty to Him; And in the strictest sense, it is a great part of Divine worship, because it is the highest exercise of Faith in God, giving the highest ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to Him. Now if this Trust be in us, it will be professed by us, being like <hi>fire</hi> there, besides we seldom or never being called forth unto it, make profession of lesse than we have, but of as much as we have, as the wicked professe more. The short of this matter is, If this <hi>Trust</hi> be in us, we cannot but make serious and hearty profession of it, engageing our selves to Him, who by His Word and Spirit wrought it in us. If our <hi>Trust</hi> be right set on God and selling, we cannot be ashamed thereof, for that shall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver make us ashamed—But so much for the clearing our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to the first Question: we proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q:</hi> II. Is this lawfull to be don?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans:</hi> We think he that makes this question is ashamed to speak it-out, <q>Is it lawfull to engage our selves to God, to be the <hi>Lords</hi> people, to walk and live as His people?</q> surely yes, and never, we think, did any one of the <hi>LORDS</hi> people make question here. Yet if he did, this may put it out of question, because The <hi>Lord God</hi> hath promised, yea sworne unto His people, He will <hi>be their God,</hi> work in them and for them, as their God in Covenant with them. It's but reason now, and altogether just, That they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:107209:10"/> should promise and sweare unto Him, to walke as His people, who have the <hi>vowes of God upon them;</hi> For can we think, and <note place="margin">Psal. 56. 12.</note> think as men, That the most High God, should bind Himself o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to His people, with His own Coards, <hi>promise</hi> and <hi>oath,</hi> those two <hi>immutable things,</hi> while yet His people stand loose from Him, <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 18.</note> not suffering themselves to be bound with the <hi>Coards of a man, with bands of love,</hi> a gracious God and mercifull Father hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for them, and calleth them, <hi>My Comandements,</hi> and <hi>My</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 11. 29, 30. 1 Joh. 5. 3.</note>
                  <hi>yoak,</hi> and makes them to all His, not <hi>greivious,</hi> but <hi>easie</hi> and <hi>light?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q:</hi> III. But may Gods people doe what they read and heare God hath don?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans:</hi> Yes; All things commanded and made possible for them to doe. In all such things, they must <hi>learne of Him,</hi> and doe as they heare and read He hath don. As in this Case, They must avow themselves His servants, as He hath vowed Himself their <hi>Lord;</hi> and to walk as His people who hath chosen them for His people, <hi>even as He walked,</hi> and <hi>follow God as deare Children,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh:</hi> 2. 6. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 1. He hath made a promise unto them, and to evidence the immutability thereof, He hath ratified it with an <hi>oath,</hi> and given witnesses and pledges, the <hi>Sunne</hi> and the <hi>Moone</hi> for the Continuance and endurance of the same thing He promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and sware unto. Surely Gods people stand bound to bind <note place="margin">Psa. 89. 34, 35.</note> themselves as strongly, as possible can be, to Him againe. And so much the rather because the <hi>flesh,</hi> the unregenerate part, in the Regenerate person is still ready to draw back, like a <hi>bullock unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>customed to the yoke,</hi> or like that which was to be <hi>bound with Cords to the hornes of the Altar.</hi> This <hi>flesh</hi> cannot abide <hi>bands</hi> and <hi>coards</hi> of Gods making, but saith still as once it did, for the flesh can speake no other language, being not of it selfe <hi>subject to the law of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 7.</note>
                  <hi>God, neither indeed can be;</hi> Let us break their bands asunder, and cast away their cords from us. The flesh is all for this and this it is craving all the day long, give me <hi>ease</hi> and <hi>liberty,</hi> though it will prove <hi>little ease</hi> anon, (which we translate <hi>Anguish,</hi> straightnesse <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 9.</note> of place) <hi>and a cursed liberty.</hi> Yet give me it saith the flesh. Truely it would endure no more than the <hi>Devill</hi> &amp; <hi>Satan</hi> would, to be bound, unlesse with its own Cords of <hi>vanity,</hi> which at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent are pleasant Coards, binding now as it would be bound; but
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:107209:10"/> anon it shall be bound as it would not, as with <hi>fetters,</hi> and <hi>held</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 36. 8. Pro. 5. 22.</note>
                  <hi>with the Cords of affliction,</hi> which it selfe hath twisted. Indeed it dearely loves, as was said, a <hi>cursed</hi> liberty, and would know no other <hi>law</hi> but that, which <hi>rules in its members.</hi> Therefore we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude; The flesh must be strongly bound to its good behaviour, there being no such professed Rebell, than this is in the whole world, or the Nationall Church there. And not to speak better of our parts than they doe deserve, as they are ours, and not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verpowred, these deserve bands too, and to be laid upon them by Him, who onely can make them binding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q:</hi> IV. Is it safe then for the people of God to lay bands or engagements upon that in them is called flesh, as, in some sense, the <hi>mind</hi> may be said to be, having something of the <hi>flesh</hi> there. <note place="margin">Col. 2. 18.</note>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans:</hi> We conceive the reason of this question is, because it is commonly said, That this laying engagements upon the <hi>flesh,</hi> and making its <hi>watch</hi> strong, is like the <hi>Law opposed to a lust,</hi> it irrita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 7.</note> and provoketh the <hi>flesh;</hi> or it is as a boundary or stop set a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst an impetuous streame, it puts some stoppage to it, but it makes the waters swell and roare; or like that restraint upon <hi>Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mei,</hi> 1 Kings 2. 36. or as we may have heard, was laid upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who was an old-man, yet never went five miles from the place he was borne, his Ruler hearing that laid a restraint upon him, that he, that would not, for after time should not; But the Man was not at rest till he had that restraint taken off. And we read what <hi>Shimei</hi> did. There is a truth in this, we like not to be bound, but then, if we lay no bounds upon the flesh, we shall run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot <hi>after the flesh,</hi> as the manner is, like a <hi>wild Asse-colt,</hi> or like a pampered horse, that hath cast his Rider; if we doe lay bands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the flesh (woe unto us if we doe not) It will fret kick and rage, and be very troublous, yet is it kept within bounds, like <hi>fire</hi> upon the hearth; but take off the bands, let <hi>flesh</hi> doe all its pleasure, what is <hi>right in its own eyes,</hi> it never doth more wrong to the soul. It will be like a fire raging upon the house-tops. We would come closer to the thing in hand.</p>
               <p>Grant we then, as well it cannot be denied, That bands laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the flesh, as the <hi>law</hi> forbidding or opposing a <hi>lust,</hi> makes the <hi>flesh</hi> for a time more impetuous and storme-like, yet doth not all this, as we conceive, so much as <hi>accidentally</hi> cause more <hi>corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:107209:11"/> in us, and procure more sin, but makes them or it more <hi>fome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> its <hi>own shame,</hi> so making sin <hi>appeare,</hi> in its likenesse <hi>sin,</hi> and become <hi>exceeding sinfull,</hi> and so, <hi>accidentally,</hi> procureth more sin (to break-out, which lay hid before) and so more <hi>guilt,</hi> and mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Condemnation. But yet all this speakes nothing, at least proves nothing against this laying <hi>bands</hi> or <hi>engagements</hi> upon the flesh, but rather is mighty through God, to prevaile with us, to make the <hi>bands</hi> firmer, and the <hi>watch</hi> stronger; Remembring this for our comfort, that the people of God are delivered from the <hi>irritating</hi> or provoking power of the <hi>Law</hi> (as well as from the Curse thereof) so far as that it shall doe them no <hi>hurt</hi> at all, but much good.</p>
               <p>So then to bring our answer nearer to the question, we say it is very <hi>safe</hi> and <hi>sure</hi> to lay bands upon the <hi>flesh,</hi> and <hi>spirit</hi> both; for, as was said, it is in some part <hi>flesh</hi> too. (1) It is <hi>safe;</hi> for the laying <hi>bands</hi> upon the <hi>flesh</hi> is the great meanes appointed by God to safeguard the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the renewed part in the <hi>New-Man.</hi> And if it be not don, and with all care and diligence, <hi>flesh</hi> will after the manner, <hi>run-riott in the day time,</hi> and like <hi>a child, sent away, or</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 29. 15.</note>
                  <hi>sent to himselfe,</hi> that is, <hi>left to himselfe, and put into his own hands,</hi> bringeth the Spirit to shame, as he, that ungoverned child, his <hi>Mother;</hi> yea and his <hi>Father</hi> too (take it in passage) though the <hi>Mother</hi> be there onely named, because she, usually, is most to blame in that matter. Therefore if we looke to find all <hi>fast</hi> and <hi>sure,</hi> shut we the gates, doores and windowes of our soules, as carefully as we doe those at night, belonging to our houses, and when we must set them wide open, set we a good <hi>guard</hi> about them, and make we our watch strong. It was spoken, in mockage, we may be serious in mentioning of it. <q>
                     <hi>See! He dares not Trust a Beleever</hi> to walke without his keeper, <hi>the law,</hi> as if he judged no otherwise of him, than of a <hi>Malefactor</hi> in <hi>New-gate,</hi> who would kill and rob if his Jailor were not with him.</q> Truely the <hi>flesh</hi> of a <hi>Beleever,</hi> and we beleeve he will say so too, is no more to be trusted than a <hi>Malefactor</hi> in <hi>New-gate;</hi> therefore he walketh not without his keeper, and he prayeth to God <hi>continually,</hi> that He would keep both him and his keeper, and then he is kept. We proceed (2) It is safe and <hi>sure</hi> for <hi>Beleevers</hi> to lay engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>flesh,</hi> for by the <hi>sure mercies of David,</hi> which never fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:107209:11"/> it is a sanctified meanes to keep all <hi>sure</hi> till they come to that <hi>inheritance, incorruptible, and undefiled, and that fadeth not away, reserved in heaven for them,</hi> where there will be no enemies to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noy them. And (3) for the <hi>Spirit</hi> renewed, so we suppose it to be, it hath its <hi>filthinesse</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 1.</note> also, even <hi>its mouth</hi> (we speak of that we call <hi>flesh</hi> in the New Creature, <hi>wherein dwelleth no good</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 7. 18.</note>) <hi>devoureth iniquity</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Pro. 19. 28.</note>; It would drink it in as greedily as a <hi>thirsty Beast water</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Job 11. 16.</note>; Therefore even the <hi>Spirit</hi> must have a <hi>guard</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged upon it also to keep it in the strength of God, fast and sure. It requireth our observation sure, as it surely argueth the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chery of our spirits, That the <hi>Holy Ghost</hi> by His Prophet makes <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 15, 16.</note> this Inference once and againe, <hi>Therefore take heed to your spirit;</hi> as if He had said, you observe nothing if you doe not observe your spirit; <hi>Therefore take heed to your spirit.</hi> We find sometimes the same words repeated <note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 19 5. 9.</note>, and then they should come with much force upon our spirits, and to ascertaine us of the good, in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it; as of the evill in neglecting of it. <hi>The dreame was dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled twice, because the thing is established by God;</hi> so, This Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is doubled; <hi>Therefore take heed to your spirit,</hi> because it is commanded and established by God, it must be so don, or else you be utterly undon. And so much to that question.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q:</hi> V. Can it be held-out from the Holy Scriptures, that this <hi>Covenanting</hi> or <hi>swearing to God to walke before Him, to keep close to Him,</hi> hath been the practise or manner of Gods people in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans:</hi> It is holy, right and good we should aske Counsell at that <hi>Abel,</hi> enquire what the <hi>Scripture</hi> saith, and so resolve our <note place="margin">2 Sam. 20. 18.</note> selves and end the matter, we will then set down some Scriptures at <hi>length,</hi> because some are so negligent, that they will not be at the labour to turne to them in their <hi>Bibles,</hi> which will informe us what the servants of the Lord have don alone, and apart, then what they have don in Company and Fellowship one with th'o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And when we have so don the Reader shall be Judge in this matter, so be he will engage in these two things, (1) That he will <hi>look</hi> into those Scriptures, so much he will doe, he may say, for it is the easiest thing in the world so to doe, to <hi>look</hi> into them. No, that is a deceit, it is the hardest thing, nay more, it is impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible for a man not changed, nor renewed, nor looking after that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:107209:12"/> glorious work, impossible for him (how sharp-sighted soever he may think himselfe, for his knowledge, learning, prudence, wisdome) to <hi>look</hi> into, that is, To understand savingly, one jote, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. 5. 4.</note> of sacred Truth. His darknesse doth marveilously benight him; <q>The corruption of his affections <hi>fumes-up</hi> into his understand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and <hi>streames</hi> in the lower faculties doe cast a <hi>mist</hi> on the higher. So then it is a conclusion of experience, That the heart must be <hi>cleane,</hi> else the <hi>Head</hi> cannot be <hi>cleare</hi> to apprehend the <hi>Truth, as it is in Jesus.</hi>
                  </q> For as long as the <hi>heart</hi> is so despe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately distempered, the <hi>Head</hi> can never be duly Disposed for the reception of such a Thing as Truth is, which is so contrary as light and darknesse are, to a wicked mans <hi>lye;</hi> we meane his <hi>whole Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> being all as his <hi>wayes</hi> are, but a <hi>lye;</hi> for as all the <hi>Popish re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> with all the <hi>Faith-devouring, and Conscience-wasting-er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours</hi> that ever the <hi>Man of sin</hi> vented to the world, are <hi>wrapt-up</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Thes. 2. 11.</note> in this <hi>one syllable or word,</hi> a <hi>lye;</hi> so also is all our Religion, as are our wayes, naught else but a <hi>lye,</hi> while we are our selves out of the <hi>way,</hi> and not changed or renewed in the spirit of our minds by the glorious work of the Spirit with His Word; Till this work be wrought, every <hi>lust</hi> in us is an enemy to every <hi>Truth</hi> as <hi>it is in Jesus,</hi> and will doe its utmost to keep it-out, that it may enjoy its selfe with more security in the dark. So then to come to a close of the first thing we would engage the Reader in, we would in the next place shew the emphasis, force, or how significant that word <note place="margin">James 1. 25. 1 Pet. 1 12. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> is, we translate <hi>look into,</hi> for it denotes such a <hi>prying</hi> into a thing, as the blessed Angells, prying into the glorious mysteries of the glorious Gospel, whereby the <hi>unsearchable Riches of Christ,</hi> are held-out to us, <hi>immortality and life brought to light.</hi> It is such a looking as Commands the bending of the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> both before the <hi>Father of spirits.</hi> And</p>
               <p>Therefore (2) He must engage to look-up and cry for that <hi>Anointing, that teacheth all things;</hi> For it is in vaine to look into these, or any other Scriptures, with-out that <hi>eye-salve,</hi> which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scales the eye, reveales the eare, opens the understanding, in a word, unvailes the heart, that we may see what we see, heare what we heare, understand what we read, all which is don by, That <hi>Guide</hi> or <hi>Interpretor onely,</hi> supposing now the Reader hath enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged <note place="margin">Act. 8. 30, 31.</note> hetherto, these are the Scriptures which we will set down at
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:107209:12"/>
                  <hi>length,</hi> as we said, and then passe on to the next Question.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>And <hi>Jacob</hi> vowed a vow saying If God will be with me, and <note place="margin">Gen 28. 20, 21 22.</note> will keep me in this way that I goe, and will give me bread to eat, and raiment to put on, <hi>then shall the LORD BE MY</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jacobs</hi> vow.</note>
                     <hi>GOD—</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And <hi>Hannah</hi> vowed a vow and said, O <hi>LORD of HOSTS,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 1. 11. <hi>Hannahs</hi> vow.</note> if thou wilt indeed look-on the Affliction of thine Hand maid, and remember me, and not forget thine Hand-maid, but wilt give unto thine Hand-maid a Man-child, then I will give him unto the <hi>LORD</hi> all the dayes of his life; there shall no Rasor come upon his head.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>I have sworne and I will performe it: that I will keep Thy <note place="margin">
                        <hi>David.</hi> vow. Psa. 119. 106.</note> Righteous Judgements.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the Saints did severally and apart; and who sees not—but we forget our selves; It is left to the Reader to judge (so he keep the Conditions,) whether it be not the Duty of Saints so to doe now?</p>
               <p>Then againe, <hi>Come with us say the wicked. Come with us, say the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 1. 11.</note>
                  <hi>Godly,</hi> let us joyne together as one Man, in one thing to promote the <hi>Glory of God, His Church, and His Truth.</hi> We beleeve veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Reader will judge it as comely for the Godly to joyne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, for God in one and the same thing, as it is for the wicked to joyne together, pla<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ted together like thornes, against God, and His Christ, and against all that which is truely and indeed <hi>Christian.</hi> Surely the Spirit of God is as prevailing (we should say <hi>infinitely more)</hi> with His servants as is the <hi>spirit of the world</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 4. 4. 5. 19.</note> with that <hi>whole world, that lyeth in wickednesse:</hi> for the evidencing of this, <hi>LOOK</hi> we, as has been said, into these Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>And they entred into Covenant, and sware unto the Lord, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Asa's</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. 2 Chro. 15: 12.</note> to seek the <hi>Lord God</hi> of their fathers, with all their heart, and with all their soule.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And <hi>Jehojada</hi> made a Covenant between him and between <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Jehojada's</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. 2 Chr 23 16. 2 Chr. 29 &amp; 30.</note> all the people, that they should be the <hi>LORDS people.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> proclaiming <hi>a Passeover,</hi> sending his posts from City to City, together with his preparations, and instructions, as to that solemne service, came-up, we conceive, to the very same thing, of making the people enter <hi>Covenant</hi> with their God. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Josiahs</hi> Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. 2 Chr. 34. 31, 32.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>King <hi>Josiah</hi> stood in his place, and made a Covenant before
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:107209:13"/> the <hi>Lord</hi> to walk after the <hi>Lord,</hi> and to keep His Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments with all his heart, and with all his soule to performe the words of the Covenant: And he caused all that were present in <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and <hi>Benjamin</hi> to <hi>stand to it.</hi> And the Inhabitants of <hi>Jerusalem</hi> did, according to the <hi>Covenant of God,</hi> the God of their Fathers.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>When <hi>Ezra</hi> had confessed, weeping and casting himselfe down before the house of God, there assembled unto him out of <hi>Israel</hi> a very great Congregation, of men and women, and <note place="margin">Ez 10. 1, 2, 3.</note> children: for the people wept sore. And <hi>Shechaniah</hi> answered and said unto <hi>Ezra,</hi> we have trespassed against our <hi>God;</hi> yet now there is hope in <hi>Israel</hi> concerning this thing. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>let us make a Covenant with our God.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>It shall come to passe in the last dayes, That the Mountaine of the <hi>Lords</hi> House shall be established in the top of the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, <note place="margin">Isa. 2. 1, 2, 3.</note> and it shall be exalted above the Hills [that is, the spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Glory and Grace of Christs Kingdome, shall be advanced above all worldly state and power] and many people shall say <hi>Come ye,</hi> and let us goe-up to the Mountaine of the <hi>Lord,</hi> to the House of the God of <hi>Jacob</hi> [that is, They shall embrace the wayes of Christ readily, freely, and willingly, yea rejoycingly.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>One shall say I am the <hi>Lords</hi> and another call himselfe by the Name of <hi>Jacob:</hi> and another shall subscribe with his hand <note place="margin">Isa. 44. 5.</note> unto the <hi>LORD,</hi> and surname himselfe by the name of <hi>Israel.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Gentiles shall come to thy light, and Kings to the <note place="margin">Isa. 60.</note> brightnes of thy Rising—</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Children of <hi>Israel</hi> shall come, they and the Children of <hi>Judah</hi> together, going and weeping, they shall goe and seek the <hi>LORD</hi> their <hi>God.</hi> They shall aske the way to <hi>Zion</hi> with <note place="margin">Jer. 50. 4, 5.</note> their faces thetherward, saying, Come and let us joyne our selves to the <hi>Lord</hi> in a perpetuall Covenant, that shall not be forgotten.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And the Inhabitants of one City shall goe to another, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, let us goe speedily to pray before the <hi>Lord;</hi> and to seek <note place="margin">Zec. 8. verses 21, 22, 23.</note> the <hi>Lord</hi> of Hosts; I will goe also.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>And it shall be, That who so will not come-up of all the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of the earth unto <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> to worship the King the <note place="margin">Zec. 14. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses 17, 18, 19, 20, 21.</note>
                     <hi>LORD</hi> of Hosts, even upon them <hi>shall be no raine.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:107209:13"/>
               <p> We humbly conceive these Scriptures speak out fully the practise of the Saints, alone and apart; and altogether when they were of one minde, heart, and judgement in the matters of their God.</p>
               <p>We suppose now the Reader that hath called for the <hi>eye-salve,</hi> will not ask for Scriptures out of the New Testament, thence to hold-out the practise of the Saints in those primitive times and ever since; because all those Scriptures cited out of the old Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, referre wholy to the manner of Saints under the New. To whom, <hi>prepared</hi> now <hi>as a Bride adorned for her husband</hi> [And a Bride among the <hi>Jewes</hi> was dressed and decked in all gayitry, her own or lent her, so that that day she appeares, a <hi>moving Mine of gold and pretious stones</hi> as we read] God hath made this Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious promise; <hi>Behold the Tabernacle of God is with men, and He will dwell with them, and they shall be His people; and God Himselfe, shall be with them, and be their God,</hi> Revel 21. 2, 3. So now we shall forbeare to mention the <hi>day of small things,</hi> as we read in the first Chapter of <hi>Johns</hi> Gospel; Nor what growth the Church had in Christs time during His personal abode with them, whereof we read, <hi>Act.</hi> 1. 15; Nor how it did encrease presently after, <hi>He was taken into Heaven</hi> with the <hi>encrease of God;</hi> nor the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <note place="margin">Joh. 14. 12.</note> of their Converse one with another, walking together in Church-Communion, whereof you may read, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. 41, 42. 44. 5. 14. 9. 31. 11. 23.—Nor will we set down here what we read in our Church Chronicles recorded of the servants of Christ in <hi>perilous</hi> or <hi>fierce</hi> times; <q>They met together every Lords day, where they could, early in the morning, and there, after mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all exhortations, and singing of Psalmes, they <hi>engaged</hi> before God each with other, in the <hi>strength of Christ</hi> to walk in <hi>All pleasing,</hi> as was comely for Saints.</q> We will conclude, <hi>There is a way of Gods worship,</hi> wherein He <hi>walks</hi> or <hi>meets</hi> with His people, and they with Him, as once it was. And it is a sad signe, <hi>That our</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 25. 22. 30. 36. 2 Cor. 6. 16.</note>
                  <hi>wayes please not God, when His wayes pleaseth not us.</hi> Therfore since His <hi>Tabernacle is with men,</hi> and they <hi>that goe not up to His feast of Tabernacles to worship the King the Lord of Hosts, upon them shall be no raine,</hi> no blessing, but barrennes and drought shall be upon them; It is time for us to look about us, and to Consider the times, and what we ought to doe. If we will not <hi>joyne our selves to the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:107209:14"/> Lord in a perpetuall Covenant,</hi> we give too cleare witnes against our selves, that we are <hi>joyned to our Idols,</hi> and little difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt us and the <hi>Anti-Christian-world,</hi> whose <hi>judgement now of a long time lingreth not, and their damnation slumbreth not.</hi> For the Righteous Lord will certainly make His <hi>threat</hi> good to th'utmost <hi>upon them shall be no raine,</hi> expounded by <hi>Isaiah</hi> Chap. 60. 12. <hi>The kingdomes and the nations which will not serve the Church shall perish: yea th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>se nations shall be utterly wasted.</hi> We proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q:</hi> VI. May not the wicked <hi>vow</hi> themselves the servants of Christ, and <hi>engage</hi> themselves the <hi>LORDS people?</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans:</hi> No, by no meanes; their engagement will not be taken; they are not <hi>free,</hi> they are engaged already, and <hi>tantum non</hi> sworne servants to other Lords, being ready servants and willing slaves to <hi>sin</hi> and <hi>Satan;</hi> These are their great Lords and Masters, Satan himselfe their Lord and their God ruling in cheife in their hearts and lives; to whom they have engaged their best service, according to the utmost of their power and skill they have and are still receiving from him. So that suppose now they should en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage to God which yet they can no more doe, than can their <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Prince</hi> of the world, but against Him: but suppose it so for teaching sake, Their <hi>Father the Devill, whose lusts they will</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 8 44.</note>
                  <hi>doe,</hi> would <hi>heare</hi> it, <hi>and could not hold his peace,</hi> but would <hi>disalow his childrens vowes in the day, that he heareth them,</hi> saying; <hi>Not</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 30. 4, 5.</note>
                  <hi>any of their vowes or of their bands, wherewith they have bound their soules shall stand.</hi> Most certainly so it would be; for as that pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sessed man <note n="a" place="margin">Mark. 5. 18. 20.</note> (though a good man, and designed for high work, to speak-forth the high praises of his God) <hi>was so exceeding fierce</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Math. 8. 28.</note>, <hi>that no man might passe by that way:</hi> and so mighty in the Devills Might, <hi>that no man could bind him, no not with chaines</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Mark. 5. 3.</note>; so is it with his children, his sons and daughters too (for <hi>he keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luk. 11. 21.</note>
                  <hi>their Pallace)</hi> If an Almighty Hand holds them not in, they will plucke asunder the chaines, and break in pieces the fetters, as burnt flax, <hi>neither can any man tame</hi> or hold them.</p>
               <p>The short of the matter is this, and the very conclusion of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience; They must be <hi>free indeed</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">John 8. 36.</note>, who indeed engage to walk as is comely for the <hi>Lords freemen</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 22.</note>; They must be <hi>living in Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>salem</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Isa. 4. 3.</note>, and <hi>free</hi> of that <hi>Mother-City</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 4. 26.</note>, who will vow themselves the servants of the living God, and live as a people, that have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:107209:14"/> themselves to the work, and service of their God. They must be well <hi>agreed</hi> that walk together. Friends of God who walk with God; as they are friends of the world, that walke with the world, <hi>according to the Course of this world, according to the Prince</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 2.</note>
                  <hi>of the power of the aire, the spirit that now worketh in the children of disobedience.</hi> In a word, They must be strengthned with <hi>All-might,</hi> who walk up to their engagement to <hi>All pleasing.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 1. 10, 11.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Here we would take-in that we have heard spoken for a wicked mans engageing to God; and Covenanting with Him.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>They have entred into Covenant willingly; or if that could not be, unless to engage with their tongues onely, yet they were <hi>forced</hi>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">2 Ch 15. 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> into it, and made to <hi>stand to it:</hi> for it must be granted that some, if not the most of them, in <hi>Asa's</hi> time, were wicked, <note place="margin">b 2 Ch 34. 3<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> yet all engaged.</q> To this we say;</p>
               <p>That King <hi>Asa</hi> and <hi>Jehojada;</hi> King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Josiah</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gageing the people to seek the Lord, and to be the <hi>LORDS peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi> to enter Covenant with Him, and to <hi>stand</hi> to it, did in so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>altogether right.</hi> And yet if our Rulers should doe so with us, they would doe <hi>altogether wrong.</hi> The Reasons, as we conceive, are these; <hi>Israel</hi> was Gods <hi>first borne,</hi> as He sayes of them; <hi>An</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 7 <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Levit. 20. 26.</note>
                  <hi>Holy people unto the Lord,</hi> the whole Nation was; They were a people <hi>SOƲGHT out,</hi> and had engaged themselves <hi>to seek the Lord;</hi> they had <hi>avouched</hi> themselves the Lords people, truely we cannot readily tell how often. But hence we conclude, Those ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Priest</hi> did their duty, in binding the people fast with their own Cords, laying them straighter and closer upon them, which they did weare too loose. Now for us, we meane the people of this Land, It is not said any where, That we are an <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly people to the Lord;</hi> Nor have we as <hi>Israel</hi> did, <hi>avouched the Lord for our God,</hi> nor <hi>sworne to seek Him;</hi> at least if so we did doe, it was not in obedience to Gods Command, nor, for the generality of us, knew we what we did. And to goe about to force us to it, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise at the best, but with our tongues, as formerly we might doe, were as hard a taske, yea as impossible, as to force the <hi>Prince</hi> of the <hi>Aire,</hi> or spirits of the world to doe it, that is, to engage to God, and Covenant with Him, who in all things stand so cross and contrary to Him. Indeed something we have heard was don at our <hi>Baptism,</hi> where the fathers and grandfathers stood (that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:107209:15"/> word some will use, and accordingly will practise) minding no more (the most of them) and understanding as little what the Minister did there, or they themselves engaged to, than did the little thing was brought thether in the Armes.</p>
               <p>We are wholy indisposed to speak more to this. So much may assure us, That they, who have made <hi>a Covenant with sin, death, and Hell, and with these are,</hi> in conceit, <hi>at an agreement,</hi> cannot possibly enter Covenant with God. The first Covenant must be <note place="margin">Isa. 28. 15.</note>
                  <hi>disanulled,</hi> disclaimed first, yea abominated, &amp; abhorred; And then they may have thoughts of entring Covenant with God. Which thing the Lords people have don, through Him, who shewed them abundant mercy, together with the <hi>iniquity</hi> of their first Covenant; and strengthned them to breake that, and to keep this. Yea He still strengthneth them to <hi>stand</hi> to their engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and to keep their vow, vowing themselves the <hi>LORDS</hi> people. We proceed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q:</hi> VII. Who is sufficient for this engageing work, to walk with God as aforesaid?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans:</hi> They and onely they who can <hi>humble themselves to</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mich. 6. 8.</note>
                  <hi>walke with their God;</hi> Can think themselves to <hi>Nothing;</hi> and doe know, that <hi>His Grace shall be sufficient for them,</hi> so as they shall <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12. 9.</note> be sure in their visible straights of invisible succours. Therefore these are still craving this grace, as an hungry-man (for they feele the want of it, for all uses and imployments, as he of his bread, and thence the spring of desire) cryeth for an Almes, or as the <note place="margin">Prov. 2. 3.</note> chapt earth (where so many <hi>clefts</hi> there are as so many tongues calling to the clouds for raine) opens its mouth for the showers <note place="margin">Tot linguae quot tissurae.</note> of heaven. So <hi>Grace</hi> must be sought for, and is by them who know what it is, and desire nothing much, but the Fountaine and <hi>Head-spring</hi> thereof, whom they cannot desire too much. <hi>Through Him they can doe All things,</hi> continually <hi>strengthning</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 4. 13. Joh. 15. 5.</note> them; <hi>without Him they can doe nothing;</hi> No, great thing, no, nor the smallest thing; not the least good motion heaven-ward; not <hi>any thing</hi> that is good: <hi>their sufficiency</hi> is of God, to Him <note place="margin">2 Cor. 3. 5.</note> they look.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q:</hi> VIII. How must this engagement be entred upon?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans.</hi> There must be serious thoughts, engageing our Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, and deliberation about it, before determination or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solution
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:107209:15"/> one way or other passe upon it. It must be taken as an <hi>oath</hi> must (for it is, if not the very same, yet is it as weighty eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry whit and momentous, nay it is a <hi>swearing to God,</hi> and must be taken) In <hi>Truth,</hi> in <hi>Judgement,</hi> and in <hi>righteousnesse;</hi> and in <hi>His</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 4. 2.</note>
                  <hi>strength</hi> alone All-sufficient for them as to the performance of it, in whom they <hi>blesse themselves, and doe glory.</hi> This is the very hinge of all, the ground and foundation where on all beareth, That this <hi>vow</hi> or <hi>Engagement,</hi> call it as you please, be undertaken <hi>in the strength of Christ.</hi> It commands all observation, which <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccles. 5. 6.</note> saith; <hi>Say not thou before the Angel</hi> [before Christ the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel of the Covenant] <hi>It was an errour</hi> [It was my ignorance what this <hi>engagement</hi> was, as to the matter or substance of it, meanes or manner of performing it, that I entred into it] <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore should God be angry at thy voyce, and destroy the work of thy hands?</hi> [as if He had said, that will not excuse thy rashnesse in suffring thy heart to be hasty to utter a thing before God: But rather such an excuse will anger the <hi>Lord,</hi> and provoke Him to accurse thee in whatsoever thou takest in hand] Therefore the people of God will put it upon their thoughts, and roule it about there, what they <hi>engage</hi> upon; what their aimes and ends are in their undertaking; and in <hi>whose strength</hi> they can performe. For they that have engaged for their own ends, and in their own strength, or not wholy in the <hi>strength of Christ,</hi> have <hi>turned back</hi> in the <hi>houre of temptation;</hi> they have <hi>dealt deceitfully, turning aside like a deceitfull</hi> or warping <hi>bow;</hi> they have growen worse after their engageing, giving cleare evidence against themselves, That they took <hi>no pleasure</hi> in God, and His matters; nor He in such <hi>fooles</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Eccles. 5. 4.</note>. And may it not be feared, at least it may be Cautioned, That some, we hope good in the maine, have put more upon their <hi>engagement,</hi> than upon Christ Himself; As some may think it e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to walke in fellowship with Gods people, though never <q>so unlike them in their walk: we meane, there may be some, who put their engagement in the roome of Christ, as if that could help them alone, or else they have made their engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment alone without their reliance upon the power of Christ. That Rule of th' Apostle, which obtaines in all Cases of Duty, doth most in this <hi>Whatsoever ye doe in word or deed, doe all in the Name of the Lord Jesus,</hi> Col. 3. 17.</q> That is, feele the need ye have
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:107209:16"/> of Christ in it; and look not that God should accept of you or your engagement, or of what else you doe, but onely through Him, <hi>in whose NAME</hi> you have don it.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Name of Christ</hi> is the very <hi>essence</hi> of all the Church doth, of all her <hi>prayers,</hi> all her <hi>praises</hi> [which are upon the matter, but so many engagements of the eye, eare, tongue, hand, and heart unto and for God] so that to pray, to praise, to engage in the Name of Christ is (1) To look up to Christ with the eye of faith, and to fix upon Him, who hath purchased this glorious privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and blessed liberty <hi>through Him to have access by one Spirit</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 2 18. 3. 12.</note>
                  <hi>unto the Father,</hi> there <hi>to speak all our mind,</hi> which is ever accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with praising of Him, and engageing to Him, and is <q>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes don in the Name of Christ,</q> that is (2) in the strength of Christ; And (3) in the virtue of the present <hi>mediation</hi> of Christ which carries this acknowledgement in it, That what we aske on earth, as to the living-up to our engagement, Christ obtaines in heaven for us.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q:</hi> IX.</head>
               <p>If this engaging to God, that is, as ye expound it, The <hi>vowing back</hi> that mercy againe to God, we have asked of Him in prayer, and received from Him, by a conscionable improvement of the same to the Glory of the Giver, which we think you called, <hi>paying our vowes:</hi> If this <hi>engaging</hi> to <hi>God</hi> (we were saying) be commanded us of God, as <hi>prayer</hi> and <hi>praises</hi> are, directly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded us in the Word; then our doubt is, and thereupon our question, <q>Whether we may <hi>vow</hi> or <hi>engage</hi> to the doing of that, which is directly commanded or forbidden in the Law of God?</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans:</hi> We would speak to this first very breifly and in a word; and then more largely afterwards. This first; That as we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, we are not to <hi>vow</hi> to God, That we will <hi>pray to Him as long as we live,</hi> and <hi>praise</hi> Him as long, because He hath heard, and we are assured, He will heare us; we are not to <hi>vow</hi> all this, because it is directly charged upon us in His Word. And yet we did not pray unto Him, nor did we praise Him, unless we did engage (1) To stir up our selves in <hi>prayer,</hi> and to <hi>watch</hi> thereunto which is to <hi>pray in prayer,</hi> we translate <hi>earnestly,</hi> or, <hi>praying in the Holy</hi>
                  <note place="margin">James 5. 17.</note>
                  <hi>Ghost;</hi> And (2) If we did not engage to God to use all possible care and diligence that what we through Christ gained in <hi>prayer</hi> from God, we would returne by <hi>praise</hi> unto Him, in a blessed im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:107209:16"/> of all for Him, through Jesus Christ our Lord. So now we come more directly to Answer the Question; wherein we will be a little larger, that we may be plainer.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>The Question is, whether we may <hi>vow</hi> or <hi>engage</hi> to doe that which is directly commanded or forbidden in the Law of God?</q> Whereto we Answer, as we are taught, <q>
                     <hi>No;</hi> We must not <hi>vow</hi> the doing of th' one or not to doe th' other; as for example, we must not vow absolutely, <hi>we will not worship Idols;</hi> That we will not <hi>sweare;</hi> That we will keep the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> observe the <hi>Lords-day;</hi> That we will honour our parents; That we will doe no murther; for all these Duties are expressly commanded by God; and therefore are past being vowed by us; onely thus we, (observing the Treachery of our hearts) may <hi>vow</hi> and <hi>engage</hi> to a <hi>greater care and stricter watch</hi> over our selves either for the doing of th' one, or not to doe th' other.</q> In a word, we may and must, vow more <hi>care</hi> and <hi>diligence</hi> in and about all those things, required of those that have subscribed their names to the God of <hi>Jacob.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus we are to understand that of <hi>Jacob,</hi> Gen 28. 21. <hi>vowing that the LORD should be his God.</hi> Also That of <hi>David, Psal.</hi> 119 106. <hi>Jacob</hi> had avowed or avouched the Lord for his God before; but then he did it with more intensiveness of spirit than before. So likewise, <hi>David</hi> had kept the words of his God before, but now he would be more strict than before in keeping of them. <q>So then, the conclusion of the whole matter is this; when <note place="margin">See <hi>Job</hi> 22. ver. 27. Mr. <hi>C.</hi> exp: there. <hi>p.</hi> 271.</note> we vow (or engage to) things already commanded or forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, we must pitch and place our vow not upon the <hi>matter</hi> of the Commandement, but upon the <hi>manner,</hi> and <hi>intensivenesse of our spirits in keeping it.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="question">
               <head>
                  <hi>Q:</hi> X. Whence is it then that we heare this Covenanting one with another, as much almost contradicted by some good men (as is meet for us to judge) as it is blasphemed by the evill?</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ans:</hi> Truely it seemes a <hi>Mystery</hi> unto us, and that enemy and adversary of all Righteousnesse, hath <hi>his hand in it,</hi> as we said, That good men should contradict it. Indeed, That wicked men should blaspheme it, that is no Mystery, for, as the <hi>works of the flesh are,</hi> it is <hi>manifest.</hi> We desire humbly to give in our perswa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion here, though we are the poorest of the flock, and the simplest
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:107209:17"/> among many, if we may be numbred amongst them; our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge is very small, the Lord knows, and hath made us to know it, to what it might have been, had we well husbanded our time, and parts, and meanes. But He knows also, That we, through the sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of the Spirit, are increasing therein, giving <hi>all diligence</hi> that way; and we trust it may be said of us, <hi>We have an unction from</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2. 20.</note>
                  <hi>the Holy one, and we know all things,</hi> cheifly needfull for us to know; we know Jesus Christ savingly, and <hi>we know that we know</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2. 3.</note>
                  <hi>Him, keeping His Commandements</hi> (in desire and endeavour) as we keep <hi>the apple of our eye,</hi> our <hi>ornaments</hi> or <hi>Jewells;</hi> or as a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note place="margin">Prov. 7. 2.</note> traveller <hi>keeps</hi> his <hi>way:</hi> we desire and endeavour with all dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence also <hi>to know Him</hi> more, and to <hi>grow in that knowledge;</hi> and <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3. <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> then we may be said truely and indeed to <hi>know all things;</hi> for <hi>He is All;</hi> All in all persons; All in all things. We will make bold <note place="margin">Col. 3. 11.</note> therefore to speak farther to this, and to tell our perswasion, and judgement in this matter; and then the Reasons why we are so perswaded, and doe so judge; first then our perswasion is, That the close of the Answer given to the <hi>ninth Question</hi> is abundantly sufficient to cut the synnewes of all that much, which alwayes hath been or now is, and still will be argued against this engaging our selves, and our best services for our Deare Lord and Christ; and against all that which is contrary to Him; and to enter into Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant each with other, and all with Him, in the <hi>power of His Might</hi> to <hi>stand to it.</hi> What more reasonable than is this? To vow (and engage to) a greater care and stricter watch over our selves; and more care and diligence in and about all those things required of all them that have subscribed their Names to Him? What more agreeing to the mind of Christ express in His Scriptures, than to vow more <hi>intensiveness</hi> of spirit in keeping to Him, and serving of Him? Surely we may vow in His Name (as before expounded) to give all diligence, that we may be <hi>fervent in spirit serving the Lord.</hi> Else, as we humbly conceive, we never make, our prayer to Him, or praises of Him, if we doe not, at the same time, engage our hearts unto him about the same thing. And then, supposing that praying and praising is an implicit kind of engageing our hearts to Him, whom we praise, and pray unto, we conclude, That what is our duty to doe every one alone and apart, is comely and decent to be don by us altogether, walking in fellowship accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:107209:17"/> to Gospel-order. We would adde a little more in prosecution of this matter, &amp; so give our reasons of our perswasion therein: and</p>
               <p>First, We may and ought, engage to <hi>stand to</hi> that <hi>Covenant</hi> made to us in Christ, comprehensively <hi>ALL</hi> the <hi>Saints salvation,</hi> and <hi>ALL their desire,</hi> because they have judged themselves <hi>meet</hi> to receive the <hi>seales</hi> thereof, having received first the <hi>witnesse of the Spirit,</hi> bearing <hi>witnesse with their spirit, that they are the children of God,</hi> Rom. 8. 16.</p>
               <p>Secondly, We may and ought engage to live-up to that <hi>Name</hi> is called upon us, <hi>of whom the whole Family of heaven and earth is</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 3. 15.</note>
                  <hi>named.</hi> This surely will be granted on all hands, That we may engage to hold-out the Name we are called by; which is but to engage in the strength of Christ, <hi>to be Holy as He is Holy; To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from iniquity; To touch no uncleane thing;</hi> for we <hi>name the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 2. 19.</note>
                  <hi>Name of Christ,</hi> and which is more, if more can be, we have His <hi>Name</hi> called upon us, and put within us. They that are true mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of That Body may be called, as we think the whole <hi>Body</hi> is, <hi>CHRIST,</hi> The <hi>Anointed of God with the Holy Ghost and with power,</hi> as the Lord Himselfe was, but in our <hi>Measure.</hi> Now if this <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 1<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Act. 10. 38.</note> be so, and we are, as we professe to be, and are Named. Then we may engage sure to a greater care and stricter watch over our selves, as was said, we may vow more intensivenesse of spirit, to live-up to our Name, to make <hi>full proofe</hi> thereof; as he that was a true Minister; so we, that are true Christians. <hi>Live-up to thy Name,</hi> saith <hi>Hierom</hi> to those he wrot unto, that had very signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant and teaching Names. Now no Name is so significant as this, or so teaching. Which remembers us of that, we have heard said of <hi>Tertullian,</hi>
                  <q>If I perceived, said he, the Man were not holy, not so much as a <hi>shew of Holiness</hi> appeares in him, or no more than a shew, by his works he denies it; of any name in the world <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Nemo Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus nisi qui placè tantum Christianus nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li enim Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus malus est.</hi> Tert As: Cap. 43. No bad manin the world, and a true Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</note> I would not name him a Christian;</q> That excellent Name would worse become him, as <hi>a Jewell in a swines snout; for Holiness is of the very essence of Christianity.</hi> A Christian without holiness, is a Christian without Christ. It is <hi>Contradictio in ad pecto,</hi> an Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man without Holiness; a gracious man without grace, as falt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out savour; a vine without fruit in the season thereof.</p>
               <p>We have told our perswasion and Reasons thereof, from the seales of the Covenant; and our Christian Name. We will for a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:107209:18"/> close of this give in here Holy <hi>Bucers</hi> lamentation, as we read it Englished unto us by Mr <hi>Palmer,</hi> whom His God hath <hi>made</hi> one of the <hi>excellent of the earth.</hi>
                  <q>Oh that we had renewed and esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blisht the Covenant of eternall life, as we have done a Civill Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. The Churches of the Martyrs were joyned together by the severe Religion of Discipline. I miserably feare what may become of our Churches, unless they are more closely graffed into Christ, and that they restore Discipline among themselves. There are some of all orders, who are against the restoring of solid fellow-ship and Discipline.</q> These are holy <hi>Bucers</hi> words, which that worthy man Englished as he saith; <q>That we, the weakest above many, and other like, as we are may observe the concurring judgements of holy men, as to this practise of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging our hearts to God;</q> and Covenanting each with other in the strength of Christ to keep them up so engaged, that when a temptation comes to take away the heart from Christ (and then the eye, eare, tongue and hand, and all are gone, when the heart is gon) we may say and say truely, every one for himselfe, <hi>my heart is engaged to Him,</hi> who asked it of me; and He hath it, and, according to my earnest desire, will keep it, engaged to Him, And all I have engaged for Him; for <hi>who made me to differ,</hi> or what <hi>have I which I have not received from Him?</hi> And Now we cannot forbeare, the <hi>love of Christ constraining,</hi> who loves a people walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">Jer. 30. 21.</note> with Him should engage unto Him, we cannot forbeare to set downe Mr <hi>Palmers</hi> own words, which being so full-up to the <hi>will</hi> of Christ, and <hi>mind</hi> of His people, shall end this matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Now as that, which is stil'd a <hi>Church-Covenant,</hi> so much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bated among the Godly, we take it to be no more, than such a <hi>mutuall agreement</hi> and <hi>joyning</hi> together mentioned, that <hi>solid fellowship and discipline may be set up,</hi> else how can there be an unity and <hi>fellow-membership</hi> in a particular Church?</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q>Say such even who dispute against this practise, <hi>This is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd in the very principles of Christianity.</hi> We then apprehend, it is not unlawfully but indeed necessary, expressly to professe what flowes from the principles of it; specially in this Case, where it is a mans own free act, that constitutes him a member of a particular Church. Such a <hi>profession</hi> and <hi>expresse consent</hi> to walk in fellowship, and to submit to <hi>Discipline,</hi> we call for.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:107209:18"/> And we beleeve without it, it will hardly be set-up unlesse a Catechisticall Answer or two of a person examin'd (though ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver so dead-hearted, and a close enemy to the power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse) shall be thought enough, which will to settle againe where we were, in old ignorance, luke-warmensse, loosnesse and formality; In stead of such as <hi>feare the Lord, walking in fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship with the Father, and one with another in the Spirit.</hi>
                  </q> We pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed in his words.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Now that any, that truely feare the Lord should stick at this, <hi>viz.</hi> to professe to own the Covenant of Gods free grace; to give-up themselves unto it, and to Jesus Christ the Mediatour of it in all His Offices; To walk under His Discipline, and in fellowship with His people; We cannot but justly wonder, and why any godly men of parts should frame and raise up <hi>bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beares</hi> against it. <hi>The Lord give them to tast the goodness &amp; sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of it, and they will be humbled before the Lord, that they ever withstood it.</hi> There is a little more; we can spare none of it. To the Novelty of this practise as it is objected to us and others we could answer at large here, That it is as old as the Gospel, for beleevers to walk together in fellowship in the duties ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed:</q> We will adde no more here; but beg the God of all Grace, That He would give us His Grace and make it sufficient for us, that we may practise according to that we have read.</p>
               <p>And now having premised these things, for the clearing our way and undertaking before us; And Commending all this he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto spoken to each others hearing, we proceed to hold forth the matter and manner of our engagement; what that is where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, in the strength of Christ, we doe engage, but this after we have shewen what did draw us thereunto; And to this, we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, we are in the first place to speak fully and clearely, as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite for us to doe in so solemne and great a matter.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:107209:19"/>
            <head>The engagement of certaine Brethren, walking under the Band of a Church-Covenant in Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel-Communion one with another.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>After they had made an humble and hearty ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of what they had received from their God, and are, by the supply of the Spirit, still receiving from Him, for their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abling to keep close unto Him.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E, whose Names are under-written, having through Him, to whom we lifted up our soules, each of us, alone and apart and altogether, beseeching Him to <hi>take us by the Armes, and teach us how to goe;</hi> Who <note place="margin">a Hos. 11. 3.</note> is <hi>All in all</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Col. 3. 11.</note>; All in all persons; All in all things, and continually strengthneth <note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 4. 13.</note>; therefore He being the <hi>strength of Israel</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam. 15. 29</note>, and the <hi>Glory of Israel</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Luk 2. 32.</note>, must have the glory of His <hi>own strength</hi> in us &amp; with us, who are <hi>Nothing</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2 Co 12. 11.</note>: having through Him, we were saying,</p>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Thought on our wayes</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Psa. 119. 59.</note>, that is, thoroughly considered them, what those wayes were, and whether they did lead, yea <hi>drive</hi> us <note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 4. 19.</note>, being our <hi>own</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Act. 14. 16.</note>, <hi>after the flesh</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Rom. 8. 13. 2 Pet. 2. 10.</note>, wayes of sin and death. And the same <hi>good Spirit,</hi> That gave us a sight of our wayes, giving us to <hi>loath</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Jer. 31, 19. Ezec. 6. 9 20 43.</note> them also, and so to <hi>leave</hi> them (for we cannot truely leave that, we doe not truely loath) <hi>turned our feet</hi> from out of those wayes, towards Himself, which before time were running from Him with our backs upon Him as the swiftest and most impetuous streame run's from the fountaine head; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we <hi>fled</hi> from Him (that is our naturall flight, and so He complaines <note n="d" place="margin">Hos. 7. 13. Zech. 14. 5</note>, <hi>they have fled from Me)</hi> like as they fled <hi>from before the earth-quake.</hi> But He, the Al-mighty God laid His <hi>Hand</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, and put forth the <hi>exceeding greatness of His power</hi> towards us, being so <hi>mercifull to us;</hi> and Called us out of our <hi>Sodom,</hi> that <note place="margin">Eph 1. 19. Gen. 19. 16.</note> horrible pit of Darkness (such it appeares to us now) that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:107209:19"/> state of Nature, or of Death, into His <hi>marveilous light</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 9.</note>; therefore it is called <hi>light</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> together <note n="b" place="margin">Isa. 60. 1, 2, 3</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Having received for our deare Lord and Saviours sake this first Grace this <hi>speciall favour</hi> (so we call it being the same He <note place="margin">Psal. 106. 4.</note> sheweth to His peculiar people) we are incited and stirred-up (hence we conclude the Truth of our Grace) to <hi>cry</hi> for more <note place="margin">Prov. 2. 3.</note> grace, more and more of the <hi>Spirit of wisdome and revelation in the knowledge of Him</hi> (for we, that have received this Grace can discerne in our selves the want of Grace which they cannot possibly doe, that wholy want it) that we may <hi>grow-up into Him</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 1. 17. 4. 15. Col. 2. 19. 2 Pet. 3. 18.</note>
               <hi>in all things, which is the Head, even Christ:</hi> For this is to <hi>grow in Grace,</hi> increasing therein <hi>with the encrease of God, to grow in the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ.</hi> A gracious man ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver sayes he has enough Grace, till Grace be consummate in Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Also.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Having this knowledge of Him, and growing therein, whereby <hi>He justifies many,</hi> even all them, and none but them, <note place="margin">Isa 53. 11.</note> that have this <hi>saving, justifying, experimental, fiduciall knowledge of Him,</hi> (for a Nationall, or speculative knowledge, a bare work of the understanding, swimming in the braine, having some light as the Moone hath, but no heat, and <hi>purifieth not,</hi> no more than a notionall or <hi>dead hope</hi> doth, causing but a wind there, <hi>which puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feth</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 8. 7.</note>
               <hi>up,</hi> no nourishment, and so is, nothing, or a thing of nought worth, nothing) but having we were saying, this knowledge of Him, we are <hi>purifying our selves, even as He is pure.</hi> We have <note place="margin">1 Joh. 3. 3.</note> also, through the same Grace, a fuller and clearer knowledge of our selves what cursed creatures we were, as all now are, while they are, as we were, <hi>with-out Him.</hi> Therefore <hi>flesh,</hi> the <hi>wisdome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 2. 12. Isa. 40. 6. Rom. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>goodlinesse,</hi> and <hi>excellencie</hi> thereof (the corruption and filthiness thereof is <hi>not to be</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>named</hi> without indignation, <hi>as becometh Saints?)</hi> though it would be <hi>trusted,</hi> for so the <hi>Bramble</hi> would, <note place="margin">b Eph. 5. 3.</note> yet <hi>no confidence must be put therein.</hi> And we beseech Him dayly, and hope in His mercy we shall hold on seeking, That He would <hi>anoint our eyes with eye-salve,</hi> that we may have a fuller sight of <note place="margin">Rev. 3. 18.</note> Him, that we may, the move <hi>love</hi> and <hi>admire</hi> Him; and a clearer in-sight into our selves, that we may more <hi>abhorre our selves,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 3.</note> (then we shall put no <hi>confidence in our selves) repenting in dust and ashes.</hi> Also</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:107209:20"/> IV. Having received this <hi>heavenly wisdome and power from</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 20. 28. 1 Tim 4. 16. 1 Tim. 3. 4.</note>
               <hi>above,</hi> to <hi>take heed unto our selves;</hi> and <hi>to rule well our own house, having our children in subjection with all gravity,</hi> we are in a good posture of spirit, through the <hi>supply thereof,</hi> (in our station, and according to our measure and gift received) to <hi>take care of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh</hi> 5. 24. 387. first impressiō.</note>
               <hi>Church of God;</hi> For, as we have learnt, <q>the same wisdome and justice, and holinesse, for kind, onely more enlarged and exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sive, acts in eyther spheare, and, will regularly move in the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and the greater house.</q> But we have experienced the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles Conclusion; <hi>He, that knowes not how to rule his owne house, cannot take care of the house of God.</hi> If we be darksome within doores, we cannot be lightsome without; for, though our light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side may be outward, yet it is dark as darkness it selfe, the more dark because we make a meere shew of light, which is not in us, <note place="margin">Joh. 3. 19.</note> but hated by us. The Truth is, If we are, as <hi>unsavoury salt</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in doores; we are the same without, and <hi>worse than Infidels</hi> in both <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 8.</note> places, for not <hi>providing</hi> things most necessary for <hi>our own,</hi> we cannot doe it for others. If we are in our own house, as a <hi>candle put under a bushel,</hi> so as we give no light to those, that are in our <note place="margin">Math. 5. 15.</note> house with us, we cannot then shine before others, as the candle does put <hi>on a Candlestick,</hi> that they may <hi>see our good workes, and glorifie our Father which is in heaven.</hi> But blessed be the <hi>God of all Grace,</hi> who hath given us <hi>more Grace,</hi> and <hi>instructed us to more discretion in this matter,</hi> so as we can, according to the Grace re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, <hi>rule our owne house, To whom be honour and power everlast<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p n="5">V. Having this in the purpose of our hearts to beg of Him [who put good motions, purposes and resolutions into our hearts, where there was not so much as a good thought before; no, but <hi>a resisting</hi> thereof, of any thing, every thing that was good; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this putting into the heart is a <hi>meere Creation,</hi> as that was, the <hi>speaking light out of Darknesse;</hi> and more wonderfull; for that darkness made no resistance but our darknesse do's, so great was our darkness] we were saying, having this in the purpose of our hearts to beg of Him, <hi>to keepe that in the purpose of our hearts,</hi> He <note place="margin">2 Chro. 29. 18.</note> hath so graciously, and as wonderfully put there (for the present preparation of the heart is of God, and this must be still begged of God to continue prepared hearts in a gracious frame), and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:107209:20"/> perswaded with us to beg this thing; and kept it in our hearts, hetherto, and we are perswaded, will so doe to <hi>the end</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 1. 8. 1 Thes. 5. 23, 24. Heb. 3. 6. 14. 6. 11, 12.</note>, we <hi>give all diligence to worke out our salvation with feare and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling,</hi>
               <q>(which affections or passions rather are two great meanes appointed of God to deliver us from two the greatest plagues, <hi>security of the flesh;</hi> and <hi>pride of spirit)</hi>
               </q> so <hi>making</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Phil. 2. 12. See <hi>Zan<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hi p.</hi> 131. 2 Pet. 1. 10, 11</note> our <hi>calling and election sure, that so an entrance may be ministred unto us abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly into the everlasting kingdome of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ.</hi> Also, and</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Lastly, Having <hi>followed us with His eye upon us</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Psal 32. 8. 34. 15.</note>, <hi>and dealt</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Jer. 40. 4.</note>
               <hi>so well with us,</hi> as to enable us to <hi>follow-on to know Him</hi> more, we apply our selves in <hi>His feare, and power of His might,</hi> to all those meanes He hath appointed for the encrease of Grace, diligently attending them in publick and in private at home and abroad, hearing the Word preached <hi>in season</hi> and <hi>out of season,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4. 1, 2.</note> (for the charge is full of Dread to the people as well as to Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters) Reading the Holy Scriptures, <hi>giving attendance to exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to Doctrine</hi> (for we think that Counsell given to <hi>Timothy</hi> is for our learning also) <hi>Meditate upon these things, give thy selfe</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 13, 14. <hi>Qui steri velit bonus, Concio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nator dei opera ut sit bonus Biblicus.</hi> Met: Ad:</note>
               <hi>wholy to them, that thy profiting may appeare to all.</hi>
               <q>He that would be a good preacher, said <hi>Musculus,</hi> must be very conversant in the Scriptures:</q> so also must he be, that would be a good Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. He cannot be an approved Teacher of others, nor can he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove himselfe taught, that is not conversant-in and studies much that sacred Book. Whence it may be so charitably judged of us, That we abominate their way and their doings, as the Devill or Hell it selfe, who speak evill of that, they have not, <hi>learning</hi> we meane; and of those they know not, and so would if they could, as others before them, of the same perswasion with them, <hi>Cecide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re presbiteros &amp; presbiterium,</hi> destroy the Ministers and Ministery both.</p>
            <p>We are Conversant also as our time and occasions can give <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> leave [for our Callings must be attended, with all care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, <note place="margin">1 Thes. 5. 14. The 3. 10, 11 Every man must have a lawfull Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, <hi>Gen.</hi> 47. 3 and must at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it with all Diligence. 1 Chro. 21. 20</note> else we should walk as <hi>unruly ones,</hi> like <hi>disorderly</hi> souldiers <hi>out of rank;</hi> Nay we should else (not <hi>providing for our own house,</hi> which we cannot doe, not attending our Callings as we ought to doe,) be worse not onely than an <hi>infidel,</hi> because the light of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth him to provide for his house, but we should be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:107209:21"/> worse than <hi>Beasts,</hi> the fowles of the Aire, and creeping things of the earth, for these provide for their own, the light of Nature teaching them; we should also, shewing the least neglect there, wrong our selves, and prove snares to others, before whom we stand charged to walk in <hi>wisdome,</hi> that <hi>without the word</hi> they may <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 5. 1 Pet. 3. 1, 2.</note> be <hi>won by our good Conversation]</hi> we were saying, as our Callings, our attendance thereupon will give us leave, we are conversant in other books, specially those, that may most concerne us, walking together in a Brotherhood, and decently in our families with <hi>a perfect heart, wisely in a perfect way;</hi> As that full and excellent <note place="margin">Psal. 101. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>Confession of Faith, held-out to us by the Assembly of Divines;</hi> with their <hi>larger and short Catechisms.</hi> Also, relating to our dayly practise, that excellent Book, that <hi>magnum in minimus,</hi> that much in a little; that greatest book in the smallest volum, Dr <hi>Owens ESCHOL.</hi> We take speciall notice also of that fourth Epistle to the Christian Reader set before the Treatises.</p>
            <p>Having now, in the integrity of our hearts, and innocency of our hands, premised all this for the reasons beforesaid: And desi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring dayly and earnestly, That all this may be much in our thoughts, and held-out in our lives.</p>
            <p n="1">I. We doe in the sight of God and Father; In the Name of His Son; and Continuall supply of the Holy Spirit, <hi>engage</hi> our selves, all we are, all we have, all we can unto Him, <hi>in whom</hi> we are by a most speciall <hi>in-Being</hi> (and not as the whole Creation is <note place="margin">Act. 17. 28.</note> in <hi>Him,</hi> and He in it, by a generall <hi>in-being,</hi> by the right of a <hi>Creator upholding all things by the word of His power,</hi> Heb. 1. 3. without which they could not but be annihilated and resolved in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their first Nothing) by a most speciall <hi>In-Being,</hi> we said, and from whom all <hi>our fruit is;</hi> and for whom as all was <hi>laid-in,</hi> and <note place="margin">Hos. 14. 8.</note>
               <hi>laid-up,</hi> so must it be <hi>laid-out,</hi> All for Him alone, as sure as He is <note place="margin">Can. 7. 13.</note> our <hi>onely Beloved</hi> and we His. And</p>
            <p>We doe (2) engage in the strength of <hi>All Might</hi> to <hi>walk</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 1. 11.</note>
               <hi>worthy of the Lord,</hi> to <hi>All pleasing,</hi> as becometh a people of His choice and care &amp; love, that are <hi>called by His Name, and wrought</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 5.</note>
               <hi>for the selfe-same thing,</hi> being planted in Him, bearing upon Him; made one with Him, and conformable to Him; and are still in the conscionable use and improvement of all His Appointments, maintaining <hi>fellowship with Him,</hi> by <hi>prayer</hi> specially, the <hi>beaten
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:107209:21"/> way of the soules Communion with God,</hi> saith one; It is a <hi>conference</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Es<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hol p</hi> 27. Mr <hi>R. <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ol. p.</hi> 55. Jud: 5.</note>
               <hi>with God, a Company-keeping with Him,</hi> saith another. Also</p>
            <p n="2">II. We doe through <hi>Him,</hi> who <hi>makes us have dominion over the Mighty</hi> [Enemies and Adversaries within and without we know not well, which are the greatest, more deadly, <hi>flesh and blood,</hi> or <hi>principalities and powers;</hi> We think, and so we speak, as those that have tasted our own thoughts, That the <hi>flesh,</hi> though so far from terriblenesse, that it is all pleasingnesse, is the most dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous and deadly enemy; for were it not for <hi>flesh in us, principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities and powers</hi> could doe us no hurt. A tryed Truth it is, that children of <hi>Anak</hi> are in this way terrible enemies, Angels of Darknesse, and sometimes turning themselves into Angels of light, standing as with their swords drawn, to keep from entring into that <hi>Narrow way;</hi> or, being entred, to walk with a <hi>right foot in it, according to the Truth of the Gospel,</hi> so holding-up to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of their God; or if none of all this, they can effect he by his own, his children by their Fathers <hi>wiles, methods,</hi> and <hi>devises,</hi> then they will cast a <hi>spewing</hi> upon the way] therefore we said, through Him, who maketh us <hi>more than Conquerours</hi> over these <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 12. Revel. 12. 11.</note> mighty enemies, in whose strength we <hi>wrestle,</hi> and by whose <hi>blood</hi> we <hi>overcome,</hi> doe engage our selves each to other as <hi>members one of onother</hi> in the same Body, whereof our Lord and Christ is the <hi>Head</hi> and the <hi>Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, To take speciall care, as of the whole Church of Christ, the Mother, and her Daughters, or sister-Churches, so far as their state and Condition can be represented to our thoughts by our eye or eare, or other wayes. And of the <hi>Word of Truth</hi> which, with the Spirit, begetts children to Her, That the <hi>everlasting Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel</hi> may spread it selfe, <hi>through the midst of Heaven,</hi> as the <hi>morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Mountaines:</hi> so also (we engage) as</p>
            <p>Secondly, To take care one of another, as <hi>fellow-helpers of the Truth,</hi> so also <hi>fellow-helpers one of another,</hi> as <hi>fellow-members</hi> use to doe. And in saying so much, and doing thereafter, we have said and don all for this <hi>Naturall</hi> caring for one the other, as the member careth for its fellow-member, <hi>naturally,</hi> sincerely, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Phil. 1. 20.</note> comprehends the whole duty required of us one towards an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. It is a walking full up in desire and endeavour, to those prescriptions set before us in Gods Word summarily, <hi>according to <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 16.</note>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:107209:22"/> this rule</hi> (which obtaines in all Cases of Duty to the Church abroad, to our enemies with-out, (for they with us are members of the <hi>politick</hi> Body) and to our Brethren within) whereafter all True Gospellers alwayes have, still doe, and still shall walke, by the good hand of God with them, walking <hi>uprightly according to the Truth of the Gospel,</hi> upon whom is <hi>peace and mercy, as upon the whole Israel of God;</hi> yet</p>
            <p>Because this feeling expression, <hi>Members one of another,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines much, yea all, that can be said in this matter, we would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist a little more upon it.</p>
            <p>This being a <hi>member of another,</hi> and dealing with him, and forth unto him as a member doth to his fellow-members, is to have the same <hi>soul with another,</hi> like <hi>minded</hi> indeed, as naturally to care for <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Phil. 2 20.</note> my Brethren, and to deale forth to them as one member deales with th' other, very studiously readily and <hi>carefully</hi> as to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> so to the Church of Christ, so to every particular member there, and <hi>wellfare</hi> of the whole and every part; he <hi>naturally</hi> careth for it; he serves the <hi>Church</hi> and every <hi>Brother</hi> and <hi>sister</hi> there, as they did, they <hi>took no gaine of money</hi> Indeed his <hi>work is</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jud. 5. 19.</note>
               <hi>his wages;</hi> The member of the Naturall body, be it the eye or hand (these are the <hi>helping members,)</hi> it is abundantly sufficient, it hath given ease and comfort to its fellow-member; To speak it in a word, If we live-up to the engagement (as through Christ we may) to care for each other as <hi>members one of another,</hi> we shall care for the Churches of Christ, &amp; for the promoting The Truths of Christ, that the Gospel <hi>may run and be glorified</hi> also, for each others wellfare; specially that our <hi>soules may prosper;</hi> we shall doe <note place="margin">3 John 2. Exod 2. 9.</note> all this as <hi>naturally,</hi> as that good Woman the Mother of <hi>Moses,</hi> took her own child, <hi>and nursed it; Ile give thee thy wages,</hi> said the <hi>Princes;</hi> No great matter whether you doe or no, thought the Mother, it shall make no difference, she had her deare child in her Armes againe, whom she feared she should never see more, and she had leave to keepe it in her house, and command to nurse it there; that was abundantly sweet wages for her sweet work; <q>How gratiously will God dispose of things, if we could leave them to His disposing. He gave His Son to the world in the <hi>fullnesse</hi> of time, so will He with Him, every other Mercy.</q> He will surely, if we can trust Him nay whether we Trust Him, or no,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:107209:22"/> He will give such <hi>Nursing Fathers and nursing Mothers</hi> to His Church, that shall <hi>care for them</hi> as <hi>naturally,</hi> as the <hi>Nurse</hi> careth for her childe, or as the Mother before-mentioned, <hi>took her child and nursed it.</hi> Also</p>
            <p>Thirdly, We engage <hi>as members one of another,</hi> against all that may hurt us; for such is the care and watchfullnes, of one mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, for and over each other, by making our <hi>watch strong</hi> against the <hi>flesh,</hi> borne with us, bred-up with us, feeding with us at the same Table, lying with us in the same bed; the worst enemy in our bosom, though seemingly our best, as it pretendeth to be, and nearest friend; Therefore against the <hi>flesh</hi> we engage our watchfullnes, as against the world and the Devill. And</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Not to meddle in matters <hi>too high for us,</hi> or which will <hi>engender strife,</hi> or <hi>doubtfull disputations;</hi> as they use to doe, who <hi>will not endure sound doctrine; but after their own lusts, heap to themselves teachers, having itching eares, turned from the Truth, and unto Fables.</hi> But we engage in the strength of Christ to <hi>watch in all things.</hi> And so <note place="margin">2 Ti. 4. 3, 4, 5.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, To <hi>save our selves from this untoward,</hi> froward, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse and crooked <hi>generation,</hi> not by leaving our places; or lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <note place="margin">Act. 2. 40. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> undon any one of those services, we, in duty, are bound to performe to those, that are <hi>with out.</hi> But by keeping our gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>pure and unspotted</hi> of the world; and girding up our loines <note place="margin">James 1. 27.</note> (for all care and diligence must be given this way) that we may be kept cleane) from the impurities, <hi>pollutions</hi> or defilements of <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 20.</note> the world we must abominate, and then we shall fly from <hi>their</hi> damnable Doctrines, and horrid practises; Those that obey not sound doctrine, we are charged, (and then we must engage to it) <hi>to note</hi> such men) <hi>and have no company with them. The companion</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Thes. 3. 14. Pro. 13. 20.</note>
               <hi>of fooles shall be destroyed.</hi> There is an elegancy here, which our English cannot reach-to. But this is to our purpose; why must a Companion of fooles be destroyed? Because he will be such an one, as vile, base, and abominable, as is he, with whom, upon choice, and with delight, he converseth. <hi>If Satan take us among his own, he will reckon us for his own, and quickly make us his own.</hi> A sad story might be told here, but dayly experience assureth it. If we will work the thing, that good is, we must depart from the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of iniquitie; <hi>Depart from mee ye evill doers: for I will keep the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:107209:23"/> Commandements of my God.</hi> We engage not to keep company with them; no <hi>not to eat</hi> with such an one, upon choice, with <note place="margin">1 Cor 5 11 2 Joh 10 11. Eph. 5. 1.</note> delight, no nor <hi>bid him God speed; For he, that biddeth Him God speed, is partaker of his evill deeds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, We engage to live as is comely for sons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; <hi>Followers of God as deare Children,</hi> calling <hi>Him Father, who, without respect of persons, judgeth according to every mans work;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 17.</note>
               <hi>and so to passe the time of our sojourning here in feare; That we may be blameless and harmless the Sons of God without rebuke in the midst of a crooked and perverse generation,</hi> amongst whom, we doe <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 15.</note> engage, in the strength of God, <hi>to shine as lights;</hi> that, as <hi>He, who</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1. 15. Eph. 5. 11.</note>
               <hi>hath called us, is Holy, so we may be Holy in all manner of conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation; having no fellowship with the unfruitfull workes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse,</hi> but by the exactnesse of our walk (for <hi>we should walk even as He walked,</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 6.) and by the Holiness of our lives, or Godlinesse of our conversation; we should (as well as with our tongues declare against sinners, which is not don but by divine assistance <note n="a" place="margin">Micah 3. 8.</note>, and so) <hi>condemne</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 11. 7.</note>, <hi>testifie</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Joh. 7. 7.</note> against, and <hi>reprove</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Micah 3. 8. 1. Pet. 2. 15. 3. 16.</note> them. For so is the <hi>will of God, that with well-doing, we should put to silence the ignorance of foolish men; having a good Conscience, that whereas they speak evill of us, as of evill doers they may be asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that falsely accuse our good Conversation in Christ.</hi> And</p>
            <p>In the last place, Because God hath <hi>heard our voyce, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined His eare,</hi> we can say, as He said, who was not more in the <hi>wayes of God,</hi> than the <hi>wayes of God were in Him</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Psal. 84. 5.</note>; for all whose strength is in the <hi>Lord</hi> as <hi>Davids</hi> was, can say as He did, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage so to say, <hi>We will call upon Him as long as we live</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Psal. 116. 2.</note>. We will never cease praying, the Command being <note n="c" place="margin">1 Thes. 5. 17</note>, (and the practise was answerable <note n="d" place="margin">Act. 10. 2.</note>,) <hi>pray without ceasing;</hi> though the words of prayer cease in the mouth, the <hi>Grace</hi> of prayer, shall not cease in the heart: For when the voice of His people cannot be heard, the <hi>voice of their breathing may. The heart has a tongue, that God can heare; and the Spirit has a tongue, which none can cut-out: when the man cannot speak, the Spirit may pray:</hi> so we are resolved, and doe engage in the strength of Christ, <hi>to call upon Him as long as we live, and to praise Him as long as we have any being;</hi> For he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, He hath enclined His eare, and heard us, granting to us, what was best for us, if not the same alwayes we asked in kind,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:107209:23"/> yet that, which was better, yea best for us; if not to our <hi>will,</hi> yet to our <hi>weal.</hi> He hath heard our prayers, therefore <hi>we will Call upon Him as long as we live.</hi> And so</p>
            <p>We doe engage to one another, to goe to God each for other, entreating Him for His Great Names sake to perfect the work He hath begun—And for His Churches, seeing our meannesse is such, for the most of us, that we cannot Contribute our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sells, nor purses, nor bodily paines, we will with all the <hi>Israel of God,</hi> engage our prayers, as a combined strength, as sure as we have <hi>set our affections that way;</hi> for no man, how poore soever in <note place="margin">1 Chro. 29. 3.</note> outwards, is poore that way, if <hi>rich</hi> in faith, and <hi>poore in spirit:</hi> we were saying, we engage to <hi>pray with-out ceasing,</hi> to the Hearer of prayers for His Churches, That He would remember them with the <hi>favour,</hi> He <hi>beareth towards them;</hi> Which He most cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly will doe. But He must be <hi>enquired off by the house of Israel</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezr. 36, 37. Isa. 60.</note>
               <hi>to doe it for them;</hi> To raise-up <hi>Zion</hi> so gloriously, <hi>That the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles shall come to her light, and Kings to the brightnesse of her Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing.</hi> And that <hi>Babylon</hi> may be cast down like a <hi>Milstone</hi> into the great waters; That the vengeance that is written, may be execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon that City of Gods Curse, by Armies <hi>chosen, called</hi> and <hi>faithfull,</hi> whose <hi>aimes</hi> shall be <hi>pure,</hi> and <hi>ends holy</hi> in shooting all <note place="margin">14. 20. Rev. 17. 14. 19. 14. Jer. 50. 14.</note> the Arrowes of Gods indignation, against that <hi>bloody City,</hi> and all those her helpers, or well willers, that cleave unto her in love, making both her and all her lovers, as we read it written, an <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horring to all flesh,</hi> chiefly because she hath <hi>SINNED A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GAINST THE LORD.</hi> As for the evill she hath don to the people of God, those execrable cruelties, she has exercised against them, and terrible wrath, whose <hi>rage went up to heaven,</hi> she hath powred out upon them. All this and much more the people of God leave with their God, <hi>to whom belongeth vengeance, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32. 35.</note> as He hath said, onely they say, as the <hi>Inhabitants of Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> are allowed to say; <hi>The violence don to me and to my flesh be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 51. 35.</note>
               <hi>Babylon. O Lord God to whom vengeance belongeth: O God to whom vengeance, shew thy selfe, shine forth clearely, lift up thy selfe Thou Judge of the earth: render a reward to the proud; LORD,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psa. 94. 1, 2, 3.</note>
               <hi>how long shall the wicked, how long shall the wicked Triumph?</hi> No longer, saith the <hi>Lord,</hi> not one minute longer, than while These Mine Enemies and Adversaries shall have made themselves meet
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:107209:24"/> for that astonishing desolation is prepared for them, <hi>filling up their measures;</hi> and I have made My people <hi>meet,</hi> for that Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous salvation, is preparing for them; and for their making them <hi>meet</hi> for it, <hi>My fire</hi> is in <hi>Zion,</hi> and My <hi>furnace</hi> in <hi>Jerusalem.</hi> So <note place="margin">Isa. 31. 9.</note> soone as this <hi>refining</hi> work is don (yet the Lord will not refine <note place="margin">Isa. 48. 10.</note> His people as <hi>silver</hi> is refined, for their dross will never out, as long as flesh is with-in, besides He will sit by them while they melt; But so soone as ever this <hi>refining worke</hi> is don, The <hi>salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> that is written shall come to <hi>Zion,</hi> flying as upon <hi>Eagles wings;</hi> for Her Lord Himselfe shall bring it, <hi>riding upon the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 33. 26.</note>
               <hi>for her Help; and in His excellency on the skie,</hi> (that is,) He will help <hi>speedily,</hi> and He will shew <hi>His state and magnificence</hi> in Helping: And as speedily, but terribly shall utter desolation come upon <hi>Babylon,</hi> as it is written, in <hi>a moment, in one day,</hi> her plagues shall come upon her in <hi>their perfection.</hi> The Lord hath said it, <note place="margin">Isa. 47. 9. Rev. 18. 7, 8.</note> and He will doe it, <hi>Travelling in the greatnesse of His strength,</hi> when He do's this thing; <hi>He will tread this wine-presse alone; His</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 63.</note>
               <hi>owne Arme shall bring this salvation; His own fury shall uphold Him; and of all the people there shall be none with Him:</hi> none; (to explaine it in passage) He shall have multitudes with Him, <hi>Armies</hi> following Him upon <hi>white Horses, called and chosen and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Revel 17. 14. 19. 14.</note>
               <hi>faithfull;</hi> And yet He <hi>treads this wine-presse alone, and of all the people there was none with Him,</hi> none to ecclipse the <hi>Glory of His wisdome, power, righteousnesse, goodnesse, mercy;</hi> All these shall be with Him but all their wisdome, is but His wisdome with them; the same may be said, of their power, goodnesse, and help, they brought in that way, all was but His help in them and with them; so that we must find at the foot of the account, <hi>Jehovah God did all;</hi> And the creature how beautifull soever with the beauty his Lord cast upon him, though a <hi>diademe</hi> and as a Crowne of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in His Lords hand, yet was he <hi>nothing;</hi> nor did he ought else at all in his own strength but sin; for which he must take to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe <hi>shame:</hi> for as sin is all the creature doth in his own strength; so shame is all he must assume to himself, giving to Him to whom it doth belong, all the Glory, for He did all. <hi>When the Day of vengeance, which is in His heart, and the yeare of His Redeemed is come,</hi> It shall appeare to all the world, That <hi>He treads the wine-presse alone;</hi> and <hi>of all the people, there was none with Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:107209:24"/>
            <p> Yet, as was said. He will be <hi>enquired off by the house of Israel to doe this for them.</hi> Therefore</p>
            <p>We engage in the strength of Christ, and as that shall come in to joyne with those, that cannot keep <hi>silence</hi> at such a time at this. <note place="margin">Isa. 62.</note> And Blessed be God, who hath <hi>wrought a people for this very thing,</hi> and gives them leave to <hi>Command</hi> Him, to wrestle with Him, and prevaile These people are acquainted with their Lords mind; He withholds that, which He is most willing to give; as we to our child, that they may tugge at it, and with strong <hi>wrestlings migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty through Him,</hi> get it from Him; He prolongeth the Deliverance, that they may prolong, and stretch-out their prayers; doe as His deare Son did, and the very same His deare children can doe, in His strength; <hi>And being in an Agonie, He prayed more earnestly;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 22. 44. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the longer that was stretched-out, so likewise was his prayer. So are the Churches prayers too, longer now than ordinary, and more <hi>fervent;</hi> Dearely bought and long a comming, is marvei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous wellcome, when it is come, and sweetest in enjoying. The summe is, and the Conclusion of all; The Churches mercies must be wrastled out of her Fathers hand, her mercies, and every one of her Childrens mercies, they must be won by prayer, and worne by praises; And blessed be God, His <hi>deare Children followers of Him,</hi> can wrestle with Him, overcome Him, <hi>Command Him,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile <note place="margin">Isa 45. 11.</note> over Him, in the power of His own might, for which they ascribe to Him all the Glory. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the summe of our engagement, who have found it in our hearts with full purpose of heart to cleave unto the Lord; and to begge his Grace continually, That He would keep it in the purpose of our hearts, so to doe, Amen, and Amen.</p>
            <trailer>An End.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:107209:25"/>
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:107209:25"/>
            <head>A Postscript.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough thus wee have spoken touching a <hi>Church-Covenant</hi> and our engageing one to th' other, in the strength of Christ, to stand thereunto; And as we have beleeved, so we have spoken, That the <hi>Oath of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> as before explained, is as much the Duty of <hi>Saints by Calling</hi> to enter-into, as to receive the <hi>seales</hi> thereof is their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge: Notwithstanding, though we, or the most of us, doe freely and heartily professe our consent to all this; yet we doe not intend it for such a necessary <hi>Test</hi> of our <hi>humbling our selves</hi> to walke with our God, as this cannot be without that; or that he, who cannot enter into it, shall not be admitted to walk with us. We cannot doubt, but that many <hi>walke humbly</hi> with their God, strengthned with <hi>All might</hi> to <hi>All-pleasing,</hi> yet never heard of a <hi>Church-Covenant,</hi> or bestowed thoughts about it. We shall not then obtrude it upon any, if we had power so to doe, for that were to reckon of it of Necessity to salvation, at least to <hi>Church-Communion;</hi> and so, perhaps, we might reflect some blame upon others, more righteous than our selves. We onely said, it is <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> and <hi>needfull;</hi> and truely we cannot conceive how matters can be carried-on, according to right order, with-out it; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to some of us, there seemes a <hi>necessitie</hi> thereof, as was said.</p>
            <p>But yet, if we shall observe in any the least Breathings after Christ, a love to Him, a delight in Him, a zeale for Him, and against all is contrary to Him, such an one should be gladly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by us, and welcomed with all acceptation, though he might, modestly, perhaps conscientiously refuse to enter a <hi>Church-Covenant,</hi> for he may scruple at it, whether there be any such
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:107209:26"/>
               <hi>Custome among the Churches of Christ.</hi> This rather is the rule we would goe-by; The <hi>Test</hi> we would take; the thing we would have made out with the tongue, and evidenced by the life, That there is <hi>Holiness</hi> at the Heart; <hi>sincerity</hi> at the bottom. And if this be made appeare, (as Holinesse with-in, will appeare with out) we aske no more for Conscience-sake, but with such an one would we walk, and would make no doubt, but he or she would be an honour to us, and an help also. And for th' <hi>other</hi> matter, it may abide leysure for farther Consideration. We would look after that in others, and no more, than what our gracious God and tenderest Father looks after in us; <hi>TRƲTH now, in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Grace,</hi> not <hi>Measure;</hi> though that should be according to that we have received; for he that soweth liberally, looks to reap plentifully; <hi>let us</hi> then, in the strength of Christ, <hi>goe-on unto perfection,</hi> such as is required of us, and accepted from us under the Grace of the Gospel; <hi>If by any meanes we may attaine unto the Resurrection of the Dead; growing in Grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ: To Him be Glory, both now and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>This onely we would add (which should have been inserted <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>line</hi> 15.) That we may <hi>call to remembrance,</hi> not onely what the Churches of Christ may now doe, as to a Church Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, their entring thereinto; But what they, with the whole nation, have don, <hi>when loe, we gave our hands,</hi> lifting-them-up to the <hi>Most High God,</hi> and <hi>did sweare,</hi> according to this forme of words, <q>We professe and declare before <hi>GOD</hi> and the world, we unfeighnedly desire to be humbled for our sins, and for the sins of these Kingdomes; especially, that we have not, as we ought, valued the inestimable benefit of the Gospel; that we have not endeavoured to receive Christ in our hearts, nor to walk worthy of Him in our lives, which are the Causes of other sins, and transgressions so much abounding among us; And our true and unfeighned purpose, desire, and endeavour for our selves, and all others under our power and charge, both in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and in private, in all duties we owe to <hi>GOD</hi> and man, to amend our lives, and each-one to goe before another in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of a <hi>Reall Reformation.</hi>
               </q> Here was a <hi>state</hi> or Nationall Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant; and <hi>loe,</hi> here is a <hi>state</hi> or Nationall <hi>breach</hi> of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:107209:26"/> for to all this (we mention but this, being to our seeming, as <hi>simple</hi> and unmixt, as <hi>Asa's</hi> Covenant was) we, all the Nation o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, lifted up our hands, but now against all this, we all, the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality, or most of us all, have <hi>lifted up the Heel;</hi> and have set our hearts against it, as <hi>firme as a stone,</hi> like the heart of the <hi>Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> as <hi>hard as a peice of the nether Milstone.</hi> As doth appeare to every eye, that hath a true discerning, and can behold our walk with in doores or without; our doings in publick or in private.</p>
            <p>Therefore will the Lord, for He is the same still reckon of us and account with us, as He hath don with <hi>mighty sinners before Him, dispisers of His oath,</hi> and <hi>Breakers of Covenant</hi> with Him; for so saith the Lord in a very like case, and as terrible the words are <hi>against a Nation,</hi> as against that <hi>man onely,</hi> seeing he despised <q>th' oath, by breaking the Covenant (when loe, he had given his hand) and hath done all these things, he shall not escape. Therefore thus saith the <hi>LORD GOD, As I live,</hi> surely <hi>MINE Oath</hi> that he hath despised, and My Covenant, that He hath broken, even it will I recompence upon his own head, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 17. 18. 19</q>
            </p>
            <p>Blessed are all the people, that shall <hi>heare</hi> and <hi>feare,</hi> be truely humbled for what they have done, if they knew not what they did; pray for Grace continually, that more may be given unto them, whereby they may be <hi>kept-back</hi> from doing any more so presumptuously as once they did, when they lifted up their hands to the <hi>Most High God,</hi> swearing to Him, to performe with Him in those things, they might know, and acknowledge to be <hi>Holy, just,</hi> and <hi>good;</hi> and yet had no purpose to doe thereafter, yea which they abhorred so to doe; others also lifting up their hands to performe those things, they were <hi>willingly ignorant of,</hi> as they were of the <hi>Law, they desired to teach, understanding the while, neyther what they say, nor whereof they affirme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Notwithstanding from hence, the Conclusion is this, <q>That if it was conceived <hi>lawfull</hi> and <hi>needfull</hi> for the <hi>Church</hi> all over the Nation, to take the <hi>Covenant of God into their mouthes,</hi> when the most of them, <hi>hated instruction, and cast His words behind them;</hi> Then may an <hi>Holy Nation, a peculiar people, who have not gon back from the Commandement of His lips: and have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed the words of His mouth more than their necessary food,</hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:107209:27"/> then may these, where ever they are, Covenant-in, and sweare to the same thing that they will be the <hi>Lords people,</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing well what they doe, and what they engage, in the strength of Christ, <hi>to stand unto.</hi>
               </q> Yet if any one, that walks humbly, in the feare of his God, be otherwise minded for the present, His God, <hi>whose he is,</hi> and <hi>whom he serveth, shall reveale even this unto him.</hi> But if he hath a mind that way, let him look round about him first, before he subscribes his Name, and lifts up his hand to the Most High God, because of this he finds writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</p>
            <p>
               <hi>When thou shalt vow a vow unto the LORD thy GOD, thou shalt not slack to pay it; for the Lord thy GOD will surely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it of thee, and it would be sin in thee.</hi> Deut. 23. 21.</p>
            <p>Reader, thou shalt now have the last words of a Dying man, and dead to thee, so soone as he has spoken them, therefore let them command thy best observation. Thou maist have met with a flat Contradiction to all our deare Lord hath said, all they also that have spoken from His mouth, in reference to all Gospel Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrations, having met with a cursed Pamphet called <hi>a legall Resolution of two important Queries,</hi> so saith the Lawyer; most illegall and irrationall will every man say that reads him, having the use of naturall Reason, not to say a sanctified understanding, as appeares all along, specially at the 11 <hi>page.</hi> where he takes his comparisons from a Gentlemans <hi>Shepherd,</hi> his <hi>Cooke, Landresse, Groome.</hi> And since he referrs thee to his foure serious Questions, you may read the marrow of them (like that in a swines bone) in a Book called <hi>foure Grand Enquiries,</hi> page 15. to page 22. And having so don, this is the earnest desire (1) that thou takest heed of putting thy finger upon the light of Reason, least the righteous God putts it quite out, as is to be feared he hath don upon this man, and those Ministers of the same judgement with him. And (2) pray for him and them, that <hi>repentance towards God, and faith towards the Lord Jesus Christ</hi> may be given them, and so the <hi>sword</hi> removed <hi>from off their Arme and right eye.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:107209:27"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>